<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A recantation of an ill led life. Or A discouerie of the high-way law With vehement disswasions to all (in that kind) offenders. As also many cautelous admonitions and full instructions, how to know, shun, and apprehend a theefe. Most necessarie for all honest trauellers to per'use, obserue, and practise. Written by Iohn Clauell, Gent.</title>
            <author>Clavel, John, 1603-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105018</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840748</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840748</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5277</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5277)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 984:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A recantation of an ill led life. Or A discouerie of the high-way law With vehement disswasions to all (in that kind) offenders. As also many cautelous admonitions and full instructions, how to know, shun, and apprehend a theefe. Most necessarie for all honest trauellers to per'use, obserue, and practise. Written by Iohn Clauell, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Clavel, John, 1603-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by William Stansby] for Richard Meighen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Clauell's recantation.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brigands and robbers --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Brigands and robbers --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:1"/>
            <p>A RECANTATION Of an ill led Life. OR A diſcouerie of the High-way Law. WITH <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ehement diſſwaſions to all (in that kind) OFFENDERS. As alſo Many cautelous Admonitions and full Inſtructions, how to know, ſhun, and apprehend a Theefe. MOST Neceſſarie for all honeſt Trauellers to per'uſe, obſerue and Practiſe.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Iohn Clauell,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>Ego non, ſum, Ego.</q>
            <q>—<hi>Quàntum mutatus ab illo?</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Approued by the KINGS moſt Excellent Maieſtie, and publiſhed by his expreſſe Commaund.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Richard Meighen,</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:2"/>
            <head>The Epistle Dedicatorie. To the Kings moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Maieſtie.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>THat you may ſee (great King) you haue not done</l>
               <l>A worke in which your glory ſhall not liue,</l>
               <l>In ſauing me: the courſe which I haue runne,</l>
               <l>Behold, deciphred, here to you I giue.</l>
               <l>In which I doe ſo punctually ſet forth</l>
               <l>Euen in the liueliest colours what I know</l>
               <l>Of thoſe baſe wayes: that who ſo has of worth</l>
               <l>The meaneſt ſparke, will ſcorne the like to doe.</l>
               <l>I haue not only charactred this ill,</l>
               <l>But Actors to; that the least iudging eye</l>
               <l>Thoſe Locusts, which your Land with trouble fill,</l>
               <l>May, in their chief'ſt diſguiſes, them diſcrie.</l>
               <l>So that in ſauing me, you haue deſtroy'd,</l>
               <l>O Heauen knowes what; a crew of thoſe vild things,</l>
               <l>By whom your better people were anoy'd,</l>
               <l>Whoſe liues may now ſpeake ſeruice to their Kings.</l>
               <l>And for my ſelfe, let my Detractors call,</l>
               <l>This courſe a ſeruile one, and to my ſhame</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5277:3"/>
               <l>Say I haue rip'd, the bowels vp of all,</l>
               <l>And to preſerue my life, haue lost my fame</l>
               <l>By ſuch detections; but (great Sir) you know,</l>
               <l>Your bountie, without article or tie,</l>
               <l>My forfeit life ſo freely did bestow,</l>
               <l>You bad, it was obey'd, I did not die.</l>
               <l>This then I pay to you a double debt,</l>
               <l>First, to that grace preſeru'd me,</l>
               <l>Next that borne dutie I must not forget which is yours:</l>
               <l>The ſubiect ow's to Princes, and their powers.</l>
               <l>The last made greater by the first: engage</l>
               <l>Both life and dutie in a two-fold band;</l>
               <l>Which may produce vnto ſucceeding age</l>
               <l>Storiet worth my redemption; which may ſtand,</l>
               <l>With the faire memories of men: ſo plac'd,</l>
               <l>The times may bleſſe your mercy; by whoſe grace</l>
               <l>This ſhame and ills of mine are quite defac'd,</l>
               <l>When vertue ſhall ſucceed in vice his place:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So that what after good my life ſhall bring,</l>
               <l>Muſt needs be call'd the bleſsing of my King.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties moſt humbly deuoted proſtitute. <hi>Iohn Clauell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:3"/>
            <head>TO HER NEVER TO BE equall'd MAIESTIE, the Queene of Great <hi>Brittaine,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>HOnours Store-houſe, Vertues Storie,</l>
               <l>Fames beſt Trophie, Natures Glorie.</l>
               <l>O may with moſſe the Muſes floud,</l>
               <l>Be ouer growne, damm'd vp with mud:</l>
               <l>All their holy Hils polluted,</l>
               <l>And their Oracles confuted,</l>
               <l>If that they ſtraine not all they may,</l>
               <l>Now their beſt vowes to you to pay;</l>
               <l>And hoarſe as Rauens may they ſing,</l>
               <l>Who dare neglect their offering;</l>
               <l>Or find a ſubiect for a Verſe,</l>
               <l>That any meaner worths rehearſe;</l>
               <l>You the true Storie are, and all</l>
               <l>That's rich, faire, ſweet, Maieſticall.</l>
               <l>The fulleſt wonder of our time</l>
               <l>For Chronicles, in Proſe, or Rime.</l>
               <l>And like the Roſie morne doe bleſſe</l>
               <l>Our drooping Land with cheerefulneſſe;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5277:4"/>
               <l>Throwing your bountie's euery where</l>
               <l>As freſh, and fragrant as the ayre.</l>
               <l>The Woodbines, and the Violet</l>
               <l>The Seaſon of the Yeare forget:</l>
               <l>And to attend your ſweetneſſe doe</l>
               <l>Grow euery where, you tread, or goe.</l>
               <l>I, in the Autume of my life,</l>
               <l>When guilt, and Iuſtice were at ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Was by your royall breath (ſtrange thing)</l>
               <l>Vnwithered, turn'd into my Spring.</l>
               <l>Accept this Sacrifice (great Queene)</l>
               <l>In which no merit can be ſeene,</l>
               <l>But that your Royall Name doe bleſſe</l>
               <l>My Muſe in her vnworthineſſe.</l>
               <l>And though no luſtre crowne my art,</l>
               <l>Holy fires inſpires my heart.</l>
               <l>Obedience, Dutie, Zeale, attend</l>
               <l>The faithfull tribute, that I ſend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So the Gods accept of ſtill:</l>
               <l>Not the off'ring but the will.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>Celuy qui plus honor vos vertus &amp; admire vostre Bonte, &amp; Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence &amp; qui eſt le plus oblige a vostre Maiestate
<signed>Iehan Clauell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:4"/>
            <head>To the no leſſe ennobled by Vertue, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Honourable by their Titles, and Dignities; the Ducheſſes, Marchioneſſes, Counteſſes, with the reſt of the moſt worthy and noble La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, of the Court of that great Queene of Mercie, her Maieſtie of Great Brittaine.</head>
            <l>THe hardeſt heart, with rudeſt hand,</l>
            <l>That is leaſt ſubiect to command,</l>
            <l>That feares not God, grimme Death, nor Hell,</l>
            <l>Nor euer knew but to rebell,</l>
            <l>Seizing by force, and rifling all</l>
            <l>That in his greedie Clutches fall,</l>
            <l>As you paſſe by, muſt in a Maze</l>
            <l>(<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oyd of all power) ſtand and gaze;</l>
            <l>Such awe a Ladies preſence beares,</l>
            <l>Filling a Rake-hells heart, which feares;</l>
            <l>Beſides, you alwayes haue your guide,</l>
            <l>And a ſafe conuoy, as you ride;</l>
            <l>Not to protect you (there's no need)</l>
            <l>Is then this Storie, (you may reade;)</l>
            <l>This chiefly is, to let you ſee</l>
            <l>My good amendments conſtancie;</l>
            <l>Our bleſſed Queene (mou'd thereunto</l>
            <l>I doe preſume, by ſome of you)</l>
            <l>Preſeru'd my life; accept you then</l>
            <l>Iuſt thankes, from my vnskilfull pen;</l>
            <l>Loe, this I was enioyn'd to write,</l>
            <l>But I meane ſhortly to indite</l>
            <l>A perfect, true, and ample Storie,</l>
            <l>That ſhall ſpeake nothing, but your glory;</l>
            <l>Accept (meane while) what heere you ſee;</l>
            <l>You'le otherwiſe, diſhearten mee.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>The admired of Vertues, <hi>Iohn Clauell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:5"/>
            <head>To the right <hi>Honourable</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> of his <hi>Maieſties</hi> moſt Honourable Priuie Counſaile, and Counſaile of <hi>Warre.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>So vild, and audacious, ſo publike, and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious haue mine offences beene; ſuch, and ſo extraordinary the mercy I haue receiued (of both which I am truly ſenſible) that I wiſh really, and ſincerely from my heart, I had ſuffered the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full death was due vnto mee, then, that now there is a faire occaſion, I ſhould bee debarred from regaining my loſt honour, and reputation, in his Maieſties Warres abroad. May it pleaſe your Honours, when I ſaw all my fellow offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and other Delinquents whatſoeuer diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged and ſent vpon imployment, I enuied not their happineſſe, but ſeriouſly began to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how I (who alone was denied that faireſt way of all) might doe my Country ſome ſeruice, euen whilſt I continued here, an vnfortunate,
<pb facs="tcp:5277:5"/> and wretched priſoner. Thus ſadly muſing (fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my Conſcience burthened,) I reſolued to write this reall <hi>Recantation</hi> of all my euill wayes; whereby I haue not only diſarmed, and preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelfe, from falling into the ſame lewd courſe of life, at any time hereafter; but alſo ſo fully and faithfully inſtructed all honeſt Trauel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, that no man that will bee pleaſed to follow my aduiſe, can from hence forth, (that way) miſcarry. Sithence therefore I haue yeelded ſo faire a teſtimonie, both of my contrition, and conuerſion; I moſt humbly beſeech your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to entertaine a fauourable, and good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of me, and (moued thence vnto commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) that you would vouchſafe to grant a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for my diſcharge, that I may not ſpend my youthfull dayes in this miſerable and wretched priſon, but may on, vpon my Prince, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries ſeruice; where I am reſolued to acquite my ſelfe, by ſome braue, and notable exploite, or a worthy death; and whilſt I liue, I ſhall at all times reſt accountable for my libertie, and the life that is lent</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours, most embounden, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and diſtreſſed Suppliant, <hi>Iohn Clauell.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Kings Bench Priſon <date>this 11. of Octob. 1627.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:6"/>
            <head>To all his Honourable, Noble, and neuer to bee enough thanked Friends at the Court.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THere's no neceſsitie that can exclude</l>
               <l>the poorest being from a gratitude.</l>
               <l>And where the ſtrength of Fortune lends no more,</l>
               <l>He that is truly thankfull, is not poore.</l>
               <l>Were I to pay this debt to courſer men,</l>
               <l>I might diſpaire; and mine owne fate contemne;</l>
               <l>Their ſatisfaction only liues in things</l>
               <l>That profit, or the Golden tribute brings.</l>
               <l>But your farre finer ſoules in Heauen that dwell,</l>
               <l>Deſpiſe thoſe meaner ends, ſo neere to Hell.</l>
               <l>And for your owne ſakes noble actions doe</l>
               <l>As well as theirs, they are extended to.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yours be the bountie then, mine the great debt:</l>
               <l>On which no time, nor power can ranſome ſet.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours moſt obliged, <hi>I. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:6"/>
            <head>To the impartiall Iudges of his Maieſties Bench, my Lord Chiefe Iuſtice, and his other three Honourable Aſsiſtants.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THoſe pardon'd men who taſte their Princes loues,</l>
               <l>(As married to new life) do giue you Gloues;</l>
               <l>But I haue choſen rather to preſent</l>
               <l>You, with the off'ring of a faire intent.</l>
               <l>And though your iuſteſt ſentence loſt it's ſcope,</l>
               <l>Yet I preſume, your goodneſſe will find hope</l>
               <l>In my vnqueſtion'd alteration: ſo</l>
               <l>You kil'd my ſin, though my life'ſcapt the blow.</l>
               <l>And that is juſtice obiect's faire extent,</l>
               <l>To iudge the Paſt, the new ills to preuent.</l>
               <l>For were the Bench of mens repentance ſure:</l>
               <l>None ſhould the ſtrictneſſe of the Law endure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So thriue this worke, as in effect it may</l>
               <l>My vice, and true repentance, both diſplay.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your distreſſed Priſoner, <hi>I. Clauell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:7"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull the Iuſtices of Peace, and Gentlemen of qualitie in this KINGDOME.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VSuall, and ordinary is your contributary charge to the reliefe of thoſe, that ſuffer loſſe by the High-way ſide (the Law requiring it) great is your care and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, almost at euery Seſſion of Aſſize, in try all of thoſe, who that way offend; ſeriouſly to bee lamented is the loſſe of many young Gentlemen (well deſcended) who haue beene, for that fact, found guilty, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly ſuffered, vntimely ignominious, yet deſerued deaths; Theſe miſchiefes, and inconueniences I haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, and ſeriouſly conſidered; ſo that (partly to exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate my owne foule offences, partly to procure eaſe vnto my burdened conſcience, but moſt eſpecially that the like may not bee hereafter) I haue written this Diſcouery, which I entitle my <hi>Recantation;</hi> I haue heereby not onely preuented the baſer ſort of people from committing ſuch rebellious out-rages, but alſo laid open to the better ſort (I meane too ſuch as are of Gentle Parentage) the foule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and baſeneſſe of the Act, that who ſo hath the leaſt relliſh of a Gentleman, will be no more ſedvced, and that way miſled; now if it take this good effect (as I heartily wiſh it may) I ſhall account my ſelfe happy, although I continue ſtill,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A diſtreſſed Priſoner. <hi>I. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:7"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhipfull, his euer deare and well approued good Vncle, Sir <hi>William Clauell</hi> Knight Banneret.</head>
            <l>YOur hidden purpoſes (graue Sir) that reſt,</l>
            <l>Within the ſecret cloſet of your breſt,</l>
            <l>Haue like predomination with my Fate,</l>
            <l>I ſhall be happy or vnfortunate,</l>
            <l>As they aſſigne me; you may iuſtly take</l>
            <l>A faire occaſion now; both to forſake</l>
            <l>And vtterly renounce me; but behold</l>
            <l>My God aboue (whoſe ſecrets are vntold,</l>
            <l>All things on Earth as he thinkes beſt decreeing,</l>
            <l>What will my future actions be, foreſeeing)</l>
            <l>Hath lent me life, and mercie, by my King,</l>
            <l>Who is his Subſtitute, in euery thing;</l>
            <l>Since then their doome is paſt, O let not me</l>
            <l>Be new arraign'd, by your ſeueritie;</l>
            <l>Forget my foule offences, me, and all,</l>
            <l>Vntill ſome braue, and noble actions ſhall</l>
            <l>Bring you a new acquainted, if againe</l>
            <l>I euer take a courſe, what ſhall be vaine,</l>
            <l>Or if of any ill, I faultie be,</l>
            <l>O then for euer diſinherit me.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your right ſorrowfull Nephew, <hi>Iohn Clauell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:8"/>
            <head>To all the graue, and learned Seriants and Counſellours at LAW.</head>
            <l>THere needs no cunning Settor to betray</l>
            <l>To his companions, when, nor yet which way</l>
            <l>You are to ride, nor need the theeues be told</l>
            <l>What ſtore of coyne you carrie; they all hold</l>
            <l>You to be rich, and certaine prize; beſide</l>
            <l>They know when from, when to, the terme you ride;</l>
            <l>Great is your danger then; which to preuent</l>
            <l>Peruſe I pray what with a faire intent</l>
            <l>Is offered to your view; if by whats here</l>
            <l>(When you ſhall be beſet) you get off cleere,</l>
            <l>My ioy ſhall be, iust like the ioy you take,</l>
            <l>When for your pleading, and good counſaile ſake,</l>
            <l>A poore man ſtill in peace retaines his owne,</l>
            <l>Who otherwiſe had beene, quite ouer throwne.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your in all due obſeruance, I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:8"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THe liuelieſt and beſt Monuments of men are their actions, and in thoſe, their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories either die before them in infamy, or ſuruiue them vnto the fartheſt extent of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuitie in the fulleſt and faireſt Regiſters of time, and glorie; both of theſe retaine their ſubſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, not in the brazen leaues of Sepulchres, nor in the tongue-failing relation of ſucceſſion, but in thoſe Paper Records, which ſeldome forfeite them to loſſe, although aſſaulted by neuer ſo many alterations, as the Stories from the firſt World, as well prophane, as diuine, may wonderfully witneſſe to all Obſeruers, This truth may queſtion my diſcretion, that haue made mine owne hand the Character of ſuch actions as Poſteritie will bluſh at, whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory might eaſily haue loſt the thoughts of men in leſſe then halfe an age. If thus I had not giuen
<pb facs="tcp:5277:9"/> it continuance as laſting as the World; It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in reſpect of my ſelfe the anſwere is difficult, but in reſpect of God, the World, and mine owne conſcience, I could contriue no fairer or more reall ſatisfaction. The ſinnes of the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt children of God haue had their like pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, <hi>Dauid's</hi> Murther and Adulterie muſt haue <hi>Dauid's</hi> written Confeſſion and Contrition, <hi>Salomons</hi> Laſciuiouſneſſe muſt haue his owne acknowledgement and recantation, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, he that is aſhamed to confeſſe the ills hee hath beene conſcious of, argues too palpably that he is a great many leagues from repentance, and is more in loue with his ſinne, then his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment. Belieue in Charitie, this is my reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that mine owne free detection of this perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and common vice, might not only kill the feare of my impoſſible relapſes, but be a iuſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrer of all the worſhippers of this courſe. Nor can I feare, that ſuch Idolatry of theirs can riſe in Iudgement againſt this truth of mine, which hath ſo honeſtly condemned them, and their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: or that their reuenges, which they haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie proclaymed againſt the innocence of my Recantation, can reach farther, then the counſels of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> Whoſe effect extended to ſelfe ruine, whilſt I ſhall be happie, to be either cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:5277:9"/> or forgotten by them; for whoſe amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I owe my Prayers, and will Religiouſly inuoke; that they may, either become new men like me, or elſe, that they may know my reſolution hath built me beyond the aſperſion of their poyſons. Nor can I feare the ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruing of this worke of mine, they that loue truth, and reconciliation of wild youth (to that perfection the firſt Creation intended) will loue my expreſſion, more then my Verſe; and hugge my intended innocence, more then they can in goodneſſe condemne my detected Offences; The reſt, that are Gald, or preuented by this Diſcouerie muſt not dare to Iudge, becauſe all indifferencie is denied them. Nor can they whoſe hatreds againſt my Perſon, or Actions, haue drawne, into a reſolued oppoſing, of my faireſt cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, clayme any Language in the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of my Booke, or profeſſion of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſince their ſplenatiue Soules will draw them into a worſe extremitie of cenſure, then euer my moſt prouoking needes could mee, into the high way of this kind of ſinning. How ſo euer it is taken, it is honeſtly meant, and will prooue (queſtionleſſe) a wholeſome
<pb facs="tcp:5277:10"/> preuention for the honeſt traueller, whoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction I couer, that my ills may finde ſome redemption that way, which is the fulleſt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and hope of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your well wiſher, <hi>Iohn Clauell.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From my lonely ſad, and vnfrequented Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> 
                  <date>October <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:10"/>
            <head>The Argument of the whole Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>AN Introduction. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 1</item>
               <item>A free acknowledgement and confeſſion of my foule offences both to God and man, with my preparation and reſolution, when I was to haue ſuffered death. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 4</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n abſolute defiance of all thoſe that follow my late courſe of life, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vpon the ſpoile. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 8</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay Law.
<list>
                     <item>1. The oath euerie young theeſe takes, when he is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a brother of the companie. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 10</item>
                     <item>2. The order preſcribed, or the charge giuen by the oldeſt theefe, to the reſt, before they attempt. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 12</item>
                     <item>3. The manner of their aſſault, and how they behaue themſelues in the action, and after. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 13</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow ſoone and ill they ſpend, what thus vnlawfully they get. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 16</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earty diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>em.
<list>
                     <item>1. By ſhewing them the miſerie of a priſon, which muſt be their firſt ſtep. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 17</item>
                     <item>2. By giuing them to vnderſtand, how much they are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in other mens opinions of them. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. By putting them in minde of their wretched and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ends (which they fondly ieſt at.) <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>As alſo of their reward in the world to come. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 28</item>
                     <item>4. That they muſt not preſume on my example of grace, which was moſt extraordinarie in many respects. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:5277:11"/>
               <item>Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the honeſt tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueller, that hee may paſſe in ſafetie.
<list>
                     <item>1. What he is to take heed vnto, before he take his iour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. How to carrie himſelfe in his Inne. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The danger of trauelling on the Sabbath day. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. How as he rides he ſhall know a theefe from an hon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> man. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. An inſtance, how dangerous it is to grow familiar wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> any ſtranger vpon the way. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. When to ride. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. Where to ride. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>8. How to ride. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>9. What is to be done, if he be beſet. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>(A foule fault whereof many trauellers are guiltie. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>10. If by chance he be vna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>es ſurprized, how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>11. Being robd, how to follow, which way to ſet for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> Hue and Cry, how to coaſt, and where to finde t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> theeues. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>An extraordinarie charge the Countrey vſually put themſelues vnto which is both needleſſe and hurtfull. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Diuers inſtructions for the Inne-keeper, how to know theeues from hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> honeſt gueſts. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.
<list>
                     <item>1. Wherein I proue my recantation to be reall <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 50, 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Wherein I anſwer ſome asperſions laid on a guiltleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> perſon, to whom I am much indebted, and how <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. Wherein I humbly beſeech his Maieſtie, to bee gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed to employ me in ſome ſeruice, and not t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> baniſh me. <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>A Poſtſcript vnto his Maieſtie for my enlargement: <hi>Folio</hi> ☞ 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5277:11"/>
            <head>CLAVELL'S Recantation.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>☞ <hi>STand and deliuer</hi> to your obſeruation,</l>
               <l>Right ſerious thoughts, that you by my relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</l>
               <l>May benefit, for otherwiſe in vaine</l>
               <l>I write, you reade, vnleſſe from hence you gaine</l>
               <l>The happineſſe I meane you; bleſt is he</l>
               <l>That will make vſe of others ieopardie.</l>
               <l>Be warn'd by me, ſo may you purchace hence</l>
               <l>At a cheape rate my deare experience.</l>
               <l>You muſt not looke from me to haue the ſtraine</l>
               <l>Of your <hi>Black-friers</hi> Poets, or the vaine.</l>
               <l>Of thoſe high flying men, whoſe rare Muſe brings</l>
               <l>Forth births, that Goſſipt are by Lords and Kings.</l>
               <l>For though I oft haue ſeene <hi>Gadd'ſ-hill,</hi> and thoſe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Red</hi> tops of Mountaines, where good people loſe,</l>
               <l>Their ill kept purſes, I did neuer climbe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pernaſſus</hi> Hill, or could aduenture time,</l>
               <l>To tread the Muſes Mazes, or their floore</l>
               <l>Becauſe I knew that they are lightly poore,</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:5277:12"/>
               <l>And <hi>Shooters</hi> Hill was fitter farre for me,</l>
               <l>Where pas'd releifes for my owne pouertie.</l>
               <l>I neuer rode on <hi>Pegaſus</hi> (for then</l>
               <l>I had fled farther then purſuite of men)</l>
               <l>If therefore you expect a loftie ſtraine,</l>
               <l>You wrong your ſelues, and me, your thoughts are vaine.</l>
               <l>Perchance my Verſe may amble, trot, or flie</l>
               <l>As if my frights preſented <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Crie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To dogge me ſtill, nor (Poet like) I faigne</l>
               <l>My theame is Truth, my ſelfe the ſubiect plaine.</l>
               <l>I cannot play the <hi>Satire;</hi> my diſguiſe</l>
               <l>Fairely pluck't off, I am no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> grim, nor wiſe,</l>
               <l>Nor curſt enough to ſcourge, no Beadle I</l>
               <l>To puniſh you with petilaſherie:</l>
               <l>I meane to paint my ſelfe, and not to be</l>
               <l>The Chronicler of others infamie.</l>
               <l>I will not ayme at Motes within your eyes,</l>
               <l>For I confeſſe in mine a beame their lies;</l>
               <l>Which I plucke out, and deale as punctually</l>
               <l>As if I ſpake againſt mine enemie.</l>
               <l>Let this inuite you then, theſe neweſt wayes</l>
               <l>Of ſelfe inuectiue writing. Now adayes</l>
               <l>Each one commends himſelfe, and others blame</l>
               <l>Of faults, when he is guiltie of the ſame,</l>
               <l>Yea; and of worſer too, and ſeeming wiſe</l>
               <l>As folly will the dainteſt Wits deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>Such has beene my conceite, for I was prone</l>
               <l>To blame each action, which was not mine owne,</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:5277:12"/>
               <l>Belieuing what I did was good, maintaining</l>
               <l>That my vngodly and worſt way of gaining</l>
               <l>Was more legitimate, and farre more fit</l>
               <l>Then borrowing, and thus I argu'd it.</l>
               <l>Who, in the way of loane, takes from his friend</l>
               <l>Whom he findes kinde, and ready for to lend,</l>
               <l>The maine of his eſtate, with an intent</l>
               <l>(Premeditated baſely) fraudulent:</l>
               <l>Betrayes a truſt, and in performance ſlacke,</l>
               <l>Breakes both his word, his owne, and his friends backe,</l>
               <l>Who findes no remedy; but who hath loſt</l>
               <l>His purſe, repayd is at the Countries coſt,</l>
               <l>Beſides the theefe ſayes not he will repay,</l>
               <l>Nor is't expected from him, and yet they</l>
               <l>That borrow, will a thouſand oaths let fly,</l>
               <l>And wiſh they may be damn'd eternally</l>
               <l>If that they faile, and thus the purſe they fill,</l>
               <l>Make light their oaths, and load their ſoules with ill.</l>
               <l>But hence capitulation, hee's not free</l>
               <l>From ill, that would by ill excuſed bee.</l>
               <l>Such Sophiſtrie as this, and ſuch beleefe</l>
               <l>The Prince of darkneſſe <hi>Satan,</hi> that old theefe</l>
               <l>Did prompt me to; he firſt perſwades to ſin,</l>
               <l>Then firmely that we may continue in</l>
               <l>The foule tranſgreſſions we commit: he tells</l>
               <l>What faire excuſe we may alledge; which quells</l>
               <l>Our good intentions to deſiſt: he ſaies</l>
               <l>Vnto the quarreller it is a praiſe</l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:5277:13"/>
               <l>For to affront the meeke, and a great glorie</l>
               <l>To boaſt thereof, and to repeat the ſtorie.</l>
               <l>The enuious, and the ſullen minded man</l>
               <l>That aimes at bloud, and ruine all he can,</l>
               <l>He cheriſhes, and ſayes it is but meet,</l>
               <l>Bids him perſiſt, and that reuenge is ſweet.</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Satan</hi> pleads, thus he deludes vs all,</l>
               <l>And then at laſt he glories in our fall.</l>
               <l>☞ But horrid <hi>Sire</hi> of Hell, I doe deſcry,</l>
               <l>And finde thou art the Father of each lie,</l>
               <l>That a delinquent has for his excuſe,</l>
               <l>And therein doth conſiſt thy maine abuſe</l>
               <l>Vnto mankinde, immediatly next that</l>
               <l>Temptation which made <hi>Eue</hi> to perpetrate;</l>
               <l>For ſince that damned act of thine, 'tis true</l>
               <l>We ſinne by nature, but are borne anew</l>
               <l>Through <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which bleſt regeneration</l>
               <l>Has notwithſtanding no relation</l>
               <l>To thoſe accurſed, that doe want the grace,</l>
               <l>For to appeale thereto: or haue the face</l>
               <l>To iuſtifie themſelues, and with a lie</l>
               <l>As'twere confront the ſacred deity.</l>
               <l>Had <hi>Adam</hi> too, not from his iuſt God ſled,</l>
               <l>Had he confeſſ'd, as otherwaies he did</l>
               <l>Denie what he had done, and had he cried</l>
               <l>For mercy, when himſelfe he iuſtified,</l>
               <l>I doe beleeue the vengeance for his ſin</l>
               <l>Had not ſo laſting, and ſo heauie bin.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:5277:13"/>
               <l>Thus I debated with my ſelfe when I</l>
               <l>Was firſt attach'd, and kept ſo priuately</l>
               <l>That none muſt viſite me, and euen then</l>
               <l>Not being allowed to haue aduice of men,</l>
               <l>To thee my gracious God I did appeale,</l>
               <l>To thee (who knew'ſt before) I did reueale,</l>
               <l>Confeſſe, acknowledge, and bewaile my ſinnes,</l>
               <l>Aſſertained that whoſoeuer winnes</l>
               <l>Mercy and fauour from thee, muſt repent,</l>
               <l>That onely cauſes thee for to relent</l>
               <l>And ſtay thy wrath, I ſaid within my heart,</l>
               <l>All idle wandring thoughts firſt ſet apart,</l>
               <l>O God moſt mercifull thou knoweſt all,</l>
               <l>What is, what was, and what hereafter ſhall,</l>
               <l>If thy foreſeeing knowledge doth deſcry,</l>
               <l>That if I liue, I will liue wickedly,</l>
               <l>And licking vp the vomit of my ſinne,</l>
               <l>The ſame or a worſe way of ill begin</l>
               <l>Now let thy thundring hand my curſ'd dayes end,</l>
               <l>But if my euill daies I ſhall amend,</l>
               <l>And by a true conuerſion yeeld thee praiſe</l>
               <l>And glory, then, O then in mercy raiſe</l>
               <l>Me from the ſnares of death, direct me to</l>
               <l>Both what I am to ſpeake, and what to doe.</l>
               <l>Thus I beſought my God; what comfort then</l>
               <l>And eaſe came to my minde, neither my pen</l>
               <l>Can write, nor you imagine, for that bliſſe</l>
               <l>He onely knowes, by whom enioy'd it is.</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:5277:14"/>
               <l>But whilſt this contemplation did tranſport</l>
               <l>My rauiſh'd minde, behold another ſort</l>
               <l>Of thoughts aſſault me, that the Deuill might</l>
               <l>Loſe all his power in me in this great fight,</l>
               <l>Me thought vpon a ſodaine I beheld</l>
               <l>My <hi>Conſcience</hi> frighted with my ſinnes, that yeld,</l>
               <l>And cry'd, accuſing me, my ills were ſuch,</l>
               <l>The glorie that I ſaw, I might not touch;</l>
               <l>The <hi>World,</hi> on th'other ſide, by me offended</l>
               <l>Inditing me, with eurdence tranſcended</l>
               <l>All trialls here, for who will not confeſſe,</l>
               <l>Addes to his fault, and doth anew tranſgreſſe.</l>
               <l>The heauenly Iudge knew all, and could enforme</l>
               <l>The Iurie how my paſſages were borne.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Satan</hi> that had tempted, next comes in,</l>
               <l>And though he faſhion'd, yet reueal'd my ſinne.</l>
               <l>So that I conſcious, all amazed ſtood</l>
               <l>Betwixt ſo much of ill, ſo much of good.</l>
               <l>And as my comforts reached at the Crowne,</l>
               <l>Frozen deſpaire aſſayes to plucke me downe.</l>
               <l>At length my ſinnes (me thoughts) like clouds did fly,</l>
               <l>And vaniſh'd quite, and none accuſer by</l>
               <l>To peale againſt my pardon, which ſeal'd ſtood,</l>
               <l>Writ in the Lambes deare innocence, and blood;</l>
               <l>And all my ruines were reſtor'd in that</l>
               <l>He that muſt iudge me is my Aduocate.</l>
               <l>And thus prepar'd, induc'd, aſſur'd, I came</l>
               <l>To my confeſſion here, reſolu'd to name</l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:5277:14"/>
               <l>And to particularize all my oftences,</l>
               <l>My ill got goods, and dearer times expences,</l>
               <l>To ſatisfie ſterne Iuſtice in each point,</l>
               <l>Vnſcruing my diſguiſes ioynt, by ioynt.</l>
               <l>Not caring though this freeneſſe might depriue</l>
               <l>My being here, and take me from the liue</l>
               <l>To mingle with the dead, if but from hence</l>
               <l>My forfeit life might pay for mine offence,</l>
               <l>I did not then vnto the Iudge at home</l>
               <l>Deny thoſe ills, which were perhaps vnknowne</l>
               <l>To his enquirle, nor refuſe to tell</l>
               <l>What euer I had done that was not well.</l>
               <l>And at the barre when death and iuſtice ſtood</l>
               <l>Not greedy for, but challenging my blood</l>
               <l>As debt to them: I did not faintly then</l>
               <l>Before the faces of ſo many men</l>
               <l>That witneſſe my arraignment, or deny</l>
               <l>My fouleſt deeds, nor could the feare to dye</l>
               <l>About me houer with a face ſo grimme,</l>
               <l>As not to eaſe my conſcience of the ſinne</l>
               <l>I had committed, that my iudgement might,</l>
               <l>How ſad ſo ere, be equall yet, and right.</l>
               <l>And that the glorie vnto God might be</l>
               <l>More then the pitie was beſtow'd on me.</l>
               <l>Nor was it hope of mercie, that my youth</l>
               <l>Might purchace fauour only for this truth,</l>
               <l>Or that the Bench in policie might ſaue</l>
               <l>Me from the clawes of death, in hope to haue</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:5277:15"/>
               <l>Such freeneſſe from the like offenders ſtill,</l>
               <l>When they ſhould ſee my plainneſſe thriu'd not ill;</l>
               <l>And that the law becauſe I vented all,</l>
               <l>Would but my follies chide, not let me fall.</l>
               <l>No, it was none of theſe, my wounded minde,</l>
               <l>That could no reſt, no eaſe, no quiet finde,</l>
               <l>But in confeſſion, plainly prou'd that I</l>
               <l>Was leſſe afraid of dying, then a lye:</l>
               <l>I knew beſides that in concealing ſo</l>
               <l>I ſtriu'd to keepe my ills, not let them goe.</l>
               <l>And he that in excuſes folds his ſhame</l>
               <l>Retaines his ſinne, although he ſaue his fame.</l>
               <l>Hence then my ill companion, I no more</l>
               <l>Will ſtriue to hide thee, but vnlocke the dore</l>
               <l>Where my offences lye, whoſe vgly ſhape</l>
               <l>Shall nor the worlds, nor mine owne cenſure ſcape.</l>
               <l>Of all the hainous facts man can commit,</l>
               <l>There's none like this of mine, for it is right</l>
               <l>Rebellion againſt God and man, ſo foule</l>
               <l>That it deſerues the loſſe of life and ſoule.</l>
               <l>☞ Now you licencious Rebels, that doe make</l>
               <l>Profeſſion of this wicked courſe, and take</l>
               <l>A pride therein, and would be term'd by me</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Knights of the Rodes,</hi> or elſe at leaſtwiſe be</l>
               <l>Stil'd <hi>High-way Lawyers;</hi> No, I doe defie</l>
               <l>You, and your actions, I will tell you why;</l>
               <l>But firſt plucke of your viſards, hoods, diſguiſe,</l>
               <l>Masks, Muzles, Mufflers, patches from your eyes,</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5277:15"/>
               <l>Thoſe beards, thoſe heads of haire, and that great wen</l>
               <l>Which is not naturall, that I may ken</l>
               <l>Your faces as they are, and rightly know</l>
               <l>If you will bluſh at what I ſpeake, or no;</l>
               <l>As well you may, but that you want the grace</l>
               <l>Forlorned men, I pitty though your caſe,</l>
               <l>Becauſe it hath been mine, and gladly I</l>
               <l>Would ſuffer death, to be a remedy,</l>
               <l>And your example, onely that I know</l>
               <l>It will doe better for to liue, and ſhow</l>
               <l>Vnto the world your baſeneſſe, to preuent</l>
               <l>Others that yet ſinne onely in intent,</l>
               <l>Conceiuing that it is a gentile courſe,</l>
               <l>Not to be diſcommended, whilſt non's worſe,</l>
               <l>Or baſer on the earth, yet it is true</l>
               <l>Some Gentlemen perhaps, before they knew</l>
               <l>The pooreneſſe of this way, to ſerue their neede</l>
               <l>Haue more then once attempted ſome ſuch deede,</l>
               <l>But now they ſee their warlike Prince take Armes,</l>
               <l>They ſcorne to liue vpon their Countries harmes,</l>
               <l>But will goe on, whence there may Honour grow</l>
               <l>To blot out quite their fames firſt ouerthrow.</l>
               <l>Expreſſing to the world, that want of Action.</l>
               <l>As much as Moneys, made them know your faction.</l>
               <l>Which though your courſer natures follow ſtill,</l>
               <l>The Actiue ſpirit leaues, and knowes it ill;</l>
               <l>But what are you, that nothing can reclaime</l>
               <l>From giuing to your ſoules ſo foule a name?</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:5277:16"/>
               <l>Who neither feare of heauens, nor earths iuſt Law</l>
               <l>Can, into compaſſe of ſelfe knowing, draw?</l>
               <l>Whoſe honours, ſtrumpetred to this baſe courſe,</l>
               <l>Haue made you of your ſelues, take no remorſe?</l>
               <l>But hugging your owne ruine, and ſoule ſhames,</l>
               <l>Are proud in loſing your repute and fames?</l>
               <l>Now I conſider better, 'tis not ſtrange</l>
               <l>That you this life will for no other change;</l>
               <l>For you haue got by this vile courſe of ſinning</l>
               <l>A kinde of ſtate, nere knowne to your beginning;</l>
               <l>And from attending others, are become</l>
               <l>The principall, and beſt men in the roome;</l>
               <l>Where (like the Aſſe in trappings) you doe awe</l>
               <l>The ſilly beaſts, that Beere and Claret draw;</l>
               <l>For they you Captaines, and Lieutenants call,</l>
               <l>And tremble when a frowne you doe let fall,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Peere</hi> leſſe now your ſelues are maſters growne,</l>
               <l>That in mans memorie were Foot-boyes knowne;</l>
               <l>And your diſpaire as baſe as your condition</l>
               <l>Makes you beleeue, if you ſhould leaue perdition</l>
               <l>In theſe attempts, you ſhould againe be made</l>
               <l>From being ſunnes your ſelues, anothers ſhade,</l>
               <l>And that your worthleſſe ſpirits cannot riſe</l>
               <l>In any courſe, that walkes without diſguiſe,</l>
               <l>For bred on dunghills, if vnmask'd, you feare</l>
               <l>You ſhall too much, in your owne filths appeare;</l>
               <l>☞ And as the witch, and damn'd Enchaunters pay</l>
               <l>Their tributes to the Deuill, and doe pray</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:5277:16"/>
               <l>In a looſe forme, vnto that beaſtly ſpirit,</l>
               <l>From whom they doe their wickedneſſe inherit,</l>
               <l>Haue their oaths, orders, and diſtinctions ſo,</l>
               <l>As they that in a tract of goodneſſe goe:</l>
               <l>Such irreligious forme, and courſe you take</l>
               <l>For your accurſed, damn'd, Protectors ſake.</l>
               <l>And fearing that your acts were not enough</l>
               <l>To make you his, an oath of ſuch blacke ſtuffe</l>
               <l>You haue compounded, as you meant to tye</l>
               <l>Your ſelues to ſinne be your owne periurie.</l>
               <l>For he that truth for ſweares, but to his ills</l>
               <l>Makes conſcience of a vow, which conſcience kills,</l>
               <l>And ſo is periur'd as he ſweares to be</l>
               <l>True to vntruths, and falſe to honeſtie.</l>
               <l>With this you tempt and binde vnhappie men,</l>
               <l>Who doubting to be damn'd, are damned then,</l>
               <l>And to thoſe vowes ſtill ſtriuing to be true</l>
               <l>Forſake all good, in being iuſt to you.</l>
               <l>This helliſh oath you miniſter, and now</l>
               <l>Out ere they ride you charme them to their vow,</l>
               <l>That if misfortune in your traffique doe</l>
               <l>Betray you to the Law, and danger too,</l>
               <l>You muſt not tell your Complices, nor name</l>
               <l>How by this curſed trade, and life you came;</l>
               <l>For if you are examin'd, when you fell</l>
               <l>To theſe lewd courſes? Then you are to tell</l>
               <l>That you came vp here with a full intent</l>
               <l>To goe for ſeruice; ere the forces went</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:5277:17"/>
               <l>(Which you muſt ready be to name) you had</l>
               <l>Spent all your money; here muſt you looke ſad.</l>
               <l>And fetch a ſigh or two, and then confeſſe</l>
               <l>Onely for one ſupply, this wickedneſſe</l>
               <l>You fell into, ſo may you moue beliefe,</l>
               <l>Whilſt you are thought to be a poore yong thiefe</l>
               <l>Lately ſeduc'd, and hence will pittie grow;</l>
               <l>Then muſt you vow you will no more doe ſo:</l>
               <l>Thus ſhall you couſin Iuſtice of her due,</l>
               <l>Quickly get off, and to this courſe anew.</l>
               <l>Nor muſt remorce of conſcience touch you, for</l>
               <l>Your ſacrament relenting doth abhorre;</l>
               <l>And (entred in) you muſt reſolue to grow</l>
               <l>Old in your Vice, and keepe your contract ſo.</l>
               <l>For you are ſworne to vſe theſe courſes ſtill,</l>
               <l>And ſo indeede are married to your ill.</l>
               <l>But be aſſur'd our Lawes are of that force,</l>
               <l>They will on eaſie ſuite graunt a diuorce.</l>
               <l>Yet you not minding this, doe next agree</l>
               <l>Both of the time, and where the place ſhall bee</l>
               <l>Appointed for a meeting, ſcarce in this.</l>
               <l>(Though in all goodneſſe ſlacke) will any miſſe.</l>
               <l>☞ So being come together, there you lie</l>
               <l>In ſome odde corner, whence you may diſcrie</l>
               <l>Such booties as ſhall paſſe, and then ſayes he</l>
               <l>That is the oldeſt theeſe, be ruld by me,</l>
               <l>And marke what I ſhall ſay, thus muſt you place</l>
               <l>Your Maskes and Chin-clothes, thus then you your face</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5277:17"/>
               <l>May ſoone diſguiſe, and what is he can ſweare</l>
               <l>Directly and preciſely who we were;</l>
               <l>And that your words may yeeld a differing tone,</l>
               <l>Put in your mouthes each one a pible ſtone.</l>
               <l>Now muſt we chuſe a watch-word ſomewhat common,</l>
               <l>As (<hi>what's aclocke</hi>) for feare leaſt we ſhould ſummon,</l>
               <l>Their thoughts into ſuſpition, then be ſure</l>
               <l>The word once nam'd, each man to deale ſecure;</l>
               <l>We that are ſtrongeſt at the gripe will ſeaze,</l>
               <l>Then be aſſur'd for to obſerue me theſe;</l>
               <l>With your left hand to catch the bridle faſt:</l>
               <l>And let the right vpon the ſword be caſt,</l>
               <l>The one preuents eſcaping, tother then</l>
               <l>Quells their reſiſtance, let our weaker men</l>
               <l>That are not thus imploy'd, cry boldly ſtand;</l>
               <l>And with their Swords and Piſtols them command,</l>
               <l>Whilſt you afright we will perſwade, ſo that</l>
               <l>By faire or foule meanes they ſhall yeeld, that's flat.</l>
               <l>☞ Perhaps Whilſt he is talking yet, one cryes,</l>
               <l>Arme, Arme <hi>Camaradas,</hi> yonder comes a prize,</l>
               <l>If vp the hill you meete, if downe they ride</l>
               <l>You follow after, and then ſide by ſide</l>
               <l>Each hauing ſingled out his choſen one:</l>
               <l>And the Coaſt cleere, you ioyntly ſeize vpon.</l>
               <l>And then in troth 'tis very ſtrange to ſee</l>
               <l>What different qualities in men there bee.</l>
               <l>You ſhall haue able fellowes, ſtrong, well ſet</l>
               <l>As cre your eyes beheld, when they are met,</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:5277:18"/>
               <l>And ſet vpon (great Boobies) tremble quiuer,</l>
               <l>And cry like Children at the word <hi>Deliuer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though to affright them there's no weapon drawne,</l>
               <l>Nor money in their purſes to be tane.</l>
               <l>Such cowards there are many, others then</l>
               <l>That are as Pigmies to theſe taller men)</l>
               <l>Though they are nere ſo threatned to be ſhot,</l>
               <l>Or to be ſtraightwayes murthered, feare it not;</l>
               <l>But fight couragiouſly whilſt they haue breath,</l>
               <l>Not daunted at the preſent ſhew of death:</l>
               <l>On diſaduantages yet being caught</l>
               <l>(Not yeelding though) by you ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theeues are brought</l>
               <l>With their ſad fellowes, likewiſe in the lerch,</l>
               <l>Out of the way, where you begin your ſearch:</l>
               <l>Then euery place about them you ſee ſift,</l>
               <l>That tis impoſſible that they ſhould ſhift</l>
               <l>A peny out of ſight: and if ſo be</l>
               <l>You find ſome gold that's quilted priuately,</l>
               <l>You call them villaines, and diſhoneſt men</l>
               <l>For their intended coozenage, happ'ly then</l>
               <l>The Traueller cryes out he is vndone,</l>
               <l>Becauſe in that all his eſtate is wonne;</l>
               <l>Which moues not, for your conſciences are groſſe,</l>
               <l>You value gaine, and not the poore mans loſſe,</l>
               <l>Then chop you Horſes moſt familiarly,</l>
               <l>Exchange you tell them is no robberie.</l>
               <l>And next moſt deſperately you make them ſweare,</l>
               <l>That they ſhall neither follow you, nor reare</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:5277:18"/>
               <l>The Country with a <hi>hue and cry,</hi> ſo vext,</l>
               <l>Robb'd, rifled, deſtitute, amaz'd, perplext,</l>
               <l>You leaue them, and are gone, they know not whither</l>
               <l>Nor ſcarce the number, but you went together,</l>
               <l>And that's all they can ſay, here is poore light</l>
               <l>To thoſe that doe purſue, yet in your flight</l>
               <l>You ſhew your cowardly feare, each Crow you ſee</l>
               <l>Seemes like a Conſtable, and if ſo be</l>
               <l>A Colt or Calfe within the buſhes ſtirre,</l>
               <l>You thinke you are beſet, in haſt conferre</l>
               <l>One with another how you ſhall get gone</l>
               <l>From that ſo imminent deſtruction,</l>
               <l>Did not I ſee of late, after a prize,</l>
               <l>A ſtrange confuſion on ſuch poore ſurmize;</l>
               <l>An Owle which into Sanctuarie gat</l>
               <l>To ſhunne the ayrie quires wondring at,</l>
               <l>Screend in a hollow Tree, ſo diſcontent</l>
               <l>Began with fatall hoopes the ayre to rent,</l>
               <l>At which you ſwitch'd apace, fearing that hollow</l>
               <l>Was of the Country, that your flight did follow,</l>
               <l>Thus more a fraid then hurt you often are</l>
               <l>The more the pitie, afterward you ſhare</l>
               <l>And doe deuide the ſpoyle, here let me ſhow</l>
               <l>Another piece of <hi>Knauery</hi> that I know,</l>
               <l>You play the double theeues, you cheate, forſweare,</l>
               <l>Reſeruing the beſt part, from thoſe you dare,</l>
               <l>And curſe your ſelues to Hell 'tis all; for I</l>
               <l>Haue found you in your damned periury,</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:5277:19"/>
               <l>☞ But makes no matter, vvhither more or leſſe,</l>
               <l>'Tis ſoone conſum'd againe in vvickedneſſe,</l>
               <l>Ill-gotten goods can neuer proſper vvell,</l>
               <l>Nor can they thriue that haue no place to dvvell,</l>
               <l>The rolling ſtone can hardly gather moſſe:</l>
               <l>Thoſe that liue on, doe alvvayes liue in loſſe.</l>
               <l>You haue no trade, no calling, no vocation</l>
               <l>Whereby to liue, and ſaue; you haue relation</l>
               <l>To nothing that is good, vvaſtfull expence</l>
               <l>Is of your lavvleſſe gaines the recompence.</l>
               <l>Thus to be furniſh'd then, is iuſt as tho</l>
               <l>A man ſhould thatch his dwelling houſe with ſnow,</l>
               <l>Which melts, drops, ſoulters, and conſumes avvay</l>
               <l>Euen the time of one ſun-ſhining day.</l>
               <l>For vvhen to Innes or Tauernes you doe runne</l>
               <l>That note your vvayes, there are you tvvice vndone.</l>
               <l>For vvell they knovv their bils you dare not chide,</l>
               <l>If you preſume your actions they muſt hide,</l>
               <l>And ſo to make them rich, you forfeit all</l>
               <l>That men may vviſe, or good, or honeſt call.</l>
               <l>And as you ſinn'd in gaining, ſo are faine</l>
               <l>To be in ſpending coozen'd, not complaine</l>
               <l>Although you knovv't, ſo thriftleſſe is their vvay</l>
               <l>That doe on ruines of their Countrey prey.</l>
               <l>I had a treble income, by the meanes</l>
               <l>Of ſuch as vvere my men, and yet my gaines</l>
               <l>Scarce counteruail'd my charge, yet vvas I vvarie</l>
               <l>Not vvaſtfull in expence, but alvvayes chairie</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:5277:19"/>
               <l>In that particular, to blinde mens eyes,</l>
               <l>For feare that thence ſuſpition might ariſe.</l>
               <l>Yet (notvvithſtanding all this thrift) I could</l>
               <l>Neuer grovv rich by ſauing, nor yet vvould</l>
               <l>The ſomme I had, vvhen I vvas doom'd to die,</l>
               <l>Pay for my buriall, and my Coffin buy.</l>
               <l>Whence I conclude, though vve goe late to bed,</l>
               <l>And riſe betimes, and likevviſe eate the bread</l>
               <l>Of carefulneſſe, the vantage vvill be ſmall</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe God giues his bleſſing there vvithall.</l>
               <l>Which he vvill neuer doe to ſuch attempts;</l>
               <l>Your vvicked and vnlavvfull courſe exempts</l>
               <l>You from that gracious benefit, and tho</l>
               <l>You doe ſubſiſt avvhile, God ſuffers ſo</l>
               <l>To try if that you vvill reclaymed bee,</l>
               <l>If not, his heauie vengeance ſhall you ſee</l>
               <l>Out poured in abundance, then too late</l>
               <l>You vvill repent you, curſing cruell fate</l>
               <l>When 'tis paſt remedie, the Pots you knovv</l>
               <l>That ouer often to the Riuer goe</l>
               <l>☞ At laſt come broken home, O then forſake</l>
               <l>This life, leaſt you your Inne the Priſon make;</l>
               <l>And here arriu'd, O Heauens; Hell not retaynes</l>
               <l>More fuller tortures, torments, vvoes, and paines.</l>
               <l>Which vvere enough to puniſh all offence</l>
               <l>Though vvith the forfeit life, the Law diſpence.</l>
               <l>For here no ſooner entred, but you meete</l>
               <l>A thouſand vvretched ſoules, that looſely fleet</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:5277:20"/>
               <l>From place, to place, where ſighing is their ayre,</l>
               <l>Their comforts coldneſſe, and their food deſpaire;</l>
               <l>And euer as they ſee a Keeper come</l>
               <l>They ſtart, as fearing ſome new martyrdome.</l>
               <l>Whilſt the inſulting Raſcall ſwels to thinke</l>
               <l>The crauen ſoule ſhould from his power ſhrinke,</l>
               <l>And ſtanding on the tiptoes of poore pride</l>
               <l>Screwes his ill fauour'd face, on tother ſide;</l>
               <l>As the poore Priſoner with a dolefull looke</l>
               <l>Seemes to petition ſome thing, (as the Booke</l>
               <l>Of his ſad face may tell) the Iayler vild,</l>
               <l>His deuilliſh heart is from remorſe exild.</l>
               <l>The minutes of your reſt (if reſt there be</l>
               <l>Within the wals of ſo much Iniurie)</l>
               <l>Are frighted with your cares, or ſome rude noyſe</l>
               <l>Of ſenceleſſe creatures, from whoſe drunken voice,</l>
               <l>The night is quartred into Earth-quakes ſad,</l>
               <l>That you would thinke eu'n the whole World were mad</l>
               <l>And you another humoriſt ſhall heare,</l>
               <l>Curſing the Stars, the Earth, and all that's neere,</l>
               <l>Another vild, and franticke in his oaths</l>
               <l>His blaſphemics 'gainſt God and Angels throwes,</l>
               <l>Curſing his cruell Creditors, and fate</l>
               <l>That makes him begge his food within a grate.</l>
               <l>Perhaps ſome pray, but if they doe, 'tis ſo</l>
               <l>As if the good they meant they did not know,</l>
               <l>But as their wants or cuſtomes doe prouoke</l>
               <l>They in diſtraction, doe their Gods inuoke,</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:5277:20"/>
               <l>Who heares as little, for ſuch vowes as thoſe</l>
               <l>The beſt effects of true petitions looſe.</l>
               <l>Here are you mingled with the various ſtraine</l>
               <l>Of fainting need, and euery humour vaine,</l>
               <l>And muſt of force endure the idle way</l>
               <l>Of thoſe that doe blaſpheme and ſuch as pray</l>
               <l>At one ſelfe inſtant, here what other ill</l>
               <l>Your owne corruption knew not, meete you ſtill,</l>
               <l>And if a little tainted when you came</l>
               <l>Ere you depart y'are all compos'd of ſhame,</l>
               <l>And grow as cunning now in all offence</l>
               <l>As he that tempted Mans firſt innocence.</l>
               <l>Nor is that humour which ſome Parents haue,</l>
               <l>(Thinking their vilder ſonnes they thus may ſaue</l>
               <l>From vtter ruine or reclayme from ſinne,</l>
               <l>If but a priſon once they are put in)</l>
               <l>To be forgiuen; for in ſauing ſo</l>
               <l>They doe precipitate their ouerthrow;</l>
               <l>The cauſe is eaſie, for examples ill</l>
               <l>Purge not, but doe adulterate the will,</l>
               <l>Too prone to giddie folly, and beſide</l>
               <l>They that enioy the ayre and Region wide,</l>
               <l>When from a Kinſman or a friend confin'd.</l>
               <l>They haue a Meſſage, or a Letter ſign'd</l>
               <l>As if they had him ſacrific'd to Hell,</l>
               <l>Nor know him, nor the place where he doth dwell,</l>
               <l>Or if they call his mention from the dead,</l>
               <l>It is as faint as of thoſe buried.</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:5277:21"/>
               <l>So that the liuing deaths of priſoners bee</l>
               <l>The feelingſt of Monuments of miſerie,</l>
               <l>But theſe are but the Interludes to thoſe</l>
               <l>Sad Tragedies writ in your ouerthrowes,</l>
               <l>And as the quickeſt paſſage in your Scene,</l>
               <l>To your Cataſtrophes, ſo ſlight, ſo meane,</l>
               <l>That he that ſees your ends, may truly ſay</l>
               <l>The Priſon was the beſt of all your play,</l>
               <l>For there your fatall lodging, and ſad roome,</l>
               <l>Preſenting to you your accurſed doome,</l>
               <l>May well inſtruct you, that abuſe of aire</l>
               <l>Hath brought you to this chamber of deſpaire,</l>
               <l>Where when the tell-tale Sunne through crannies ſpies</l>
               <l>Your day-bard carkaſſe, lock'd in miſeries,</l>
               <l>It ſnatches his free beames from your dull ſight,</l>
               <l>As who ſhould ſay, you had abus'd his light</l>
               <l>By doing that it was aſham'd to ſee,</l>
               <l>And therefore darkneſſe muſt your portion bee.</l>
               <l>The night, which you can ſcarce diſtinguiſh then,</l>
               <l>(Whilſt your ſad thoughts your errours may condemne)</l>
               <l>Inſtead of ſleepe, ſhould with a thouſand feares,</l>
               <l>Sound your wak'd conſcience larums in your eares,</l>
               <l>Vnfold your guilts, and crowne your watchfull eyes</l>
               <l>Not with a dreame, but ſence of Miſeries,</l>
               <l>Then death, which or you feare not, or deſpiſe</l>
               <l>Muſt coldly in your apprehenſions riſe,</l>
               <l>And teach you truly what it is to die,</l>
               <l>Not natures, but the ſonnes of infamie.</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5277:21"/>
               <l>☞ But ſuch conſiderations haue long ſince,</l>
               <l>With your worſt thoughts, a cruell difference.</l>
               <l>For you beleeue you haue deſeru'd to bee</l>
               <l>Admir'd, not ſcorn'd, for your paſt villany,</l>
               <l>And that the actions, you haue done are ſuch</l>
               <l>As pace with honour, can endure the touch</l>
               <l>Of cruell'ſt cenſure, whilſt you fondly deeme</l>
               <l>That men you braue, and valiant doe eſteeme,</l>
               <l>And ſo are bound with your ills to conniue,</l>
               <l>And in deſpight of Law keepe you aliue.</l>
               <l>So from the Gaole vnto the halter goe</l>
               <l>Careleſſe of now, or after ouerthrow.</l>
               <l>Baſe vſurpation, and conceits as vaine</l>
               <l>As are your liues, expenſes, and your gaine.</l>
               <l>For good and braue men cenſure right your ſinne,</l>
               <l>And pitty you, and the courſe you are in</l>
               <l>Rather in common Pietie, then that</l>
               <l>Your vilde defeatings ſhould be wondred at;</l>
               <l>And ſince you are diſcouered thus by mee,</l>
               <l>If by miſtake before a man might bee</l>
               <l>So cheated with your boaſtings, and lowd talke,</l>
               <l>Becauſe he neuer knew the tracke you walke</l>
               <l>With your diſguiſes, now his Iudgement may</l>
               <l>Be altered, betterd, or quite throwne away.</l>
               <l>When all your fained worths, appeare to be,</l>
               <l>But faint protectors of your infamy</l>
               <l>Diſabled in the poore things you commit,</l>
               <l>Which neither are for worth, nor valour fit.</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:5277:22"/>
               <l>Your ends beſides (if nothing elſe) might draw</l>
               <l>☞ You into feare to breake the rigorous Law;</l>
               <l>Vnhappie he that hangs vpon a tree,</l>
               <l>The wretched guerdon of impietie.</l>
               <l>Nor Dyes the ſhame with him that ſuffers ſo,</l>
               <l>His family in ſuch an ouerthrow</l>
               <l>Participate and ſhare, whoſe innocence</l>
               <l>Are Dyed in ſcandall, but for his offence.</l>
               <l>And the whole ſtocke, aboue an age in time,</l>
               <l>Is blaſted for this debt, he paid his crime.</l>
               <l>And yet theſe ſenceleſſe Caitiues who inherit</l>
               <l>This way of dying by their owne demerit,</l>
               <l>Laugh at this Iudgement, call it a fine thing.</l>
               <l>Thus to be pulld to heauen in a ſtringe,</l>
               <l>And that the Apoplex, fleames and Catarre,</l>
               <l>More cruell to the ſoules of Chriſtians are</l>
               <l>Then hanging, for theſe paſſions take men hence,</l>
               <l>Ere they can thinke of dying, or haue ſence</l>
               <l>Of their repentance, being ſnatcht away</l>
               <l>Scarce with ſo poore a warning, as to pray.</l>
               <l>But theſe haue Sermons, prayer, Sacrament,</l>
               <l>Pſalmes, and alwayes to bring them to repent,</l>
               <l>And a great audience of the people by.</l>
               <l>For whoſe faire warning th'are content to dy,</l>
               <l>And thus their ſtrong deluder drawes them on</l>
               <l>To laugh at, and deſerues deſtruction.</l>
               <l>What ſhould be their example, and afright them</l>
               <l>Doe rather pleaſe, reioyce, content, delight them,</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:5277:22"/>
               <l>☞ But you fond men it may be doe ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>Becauſe I ſcap'd, that you ſhall neither looſe</l>
               <l>Your forfeit liues, I wiſh the grace I found</l>
               <l>May not to any of your harmes redownd,</l>
               <l>I meane to your encouragement, you know</l>
               <l>But of particulars no generalls grow,</l>
               <l>One Swallow makes no Summer, though <hi>Noyes</hi> flood</l>
               <l>Once ouerwhelmed all the liuing brood</l>
               <l>That ſtroue againſt the ſtreame, topping the rankes</l>
               <l>Of the great Mountaines, and the leſſer <hi>Bankes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With euery <hi>Grawling</hi> creature (not one miſt)</l>
               <l>Though they <hi>Lent all</hi> their powers to reſiſt,</l>
               <l>Yet God hath promiſed (we haue vnderſtood)</l>
               <l>He will not ſend vs ſuch another flood.</l>
               <l>Things ſeldome are not vſuall: beſides ſtrong</l>
               <l>The reaſons are, that did my life prolong</l>
               <l>You muſt conclude, that had the time not byn</l>
               <l>The Iubily of mercy, when my ſinne</l>
               <l>Was cald in queſtion, I had preſident</l>
               <l>Bin not in writing, but in puniſhment:</l>
               <l>For that great power by whom we gouern'd are,</l>
               <l>To limit my ill courſes (ſtraind ſo farre)</l>
               <l>Thus tooke me from my ſinne, and did contriue</l>
               <l>How by ſtrange meanes I ſhould be kept aliue,</l>
               <l>For know, iuſt at that inſtant when the ioyes</l>
               <l>Of great men, good men, old men, young men, Boyes,</l>
               <l>Had but one obiect, like the heauenly ſpheares,</l>
               <l>Whoſe harmony, one note, one burthen beares,</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:5277:23"/>
               <l>Then when each face did like a Bridegroome ſmile,</l>
               <l>And one entire contentment crown'd this Iſle,</l>
               <l>The Birds, the Beaſts, the men, and euery thing</l>
               <l>Preſenting their glad <hi>Aues</hi> to their king,</l>
               <l>Who like a Sunne new riſen on the earth,</l>
               <l>Diſdaines to view a corner where's not mirth,</l>
               <l>So threw a beame on me, whoſe luckleſſe fate</l>
               <l>Was then midſt all this ioy diſconſolate.</l>
               <l>Then was my apprehenſion, euen iuſt then</l>
               <l>As if my faults diſtinguiſh'd me from men</l>
               <l>That were ordain'd for ioy, or mine offence</l>
               <l>Deny'd my ſhare in bliſſe of Innocence.</l>
               <l>Yet this preſeru'd me; <hi>Barabbas</hi> muſt be</l>
               <l>At the great Feaſt from death and bondage free,</l>
               <l>It was no fauour to the man, or crime,</l>
               <l>That ſau'd his life, his bleſſing was the time,</l>
               <l>Nor could my glorious Sunne, that Roſe ſo faire,</l>
               <l>With blood infect or cloud the laughing aire,</l>
               <l>Or die the Crimſon of his Morne with red</l>
               <l>Of Malefactors blood (ſo early ſhed)</l>
               <l>His beauty is his owne, nor would he ſhine</l>
               <l>At firſt in Iuſtice, though 'tis cald diuine.</l>
               <l>Hence grew the Mercy, that my ioy ſo might</l>
               <l>Be in reſpect of all mens tripartite,</l>
               <l>For beſides this I had an Aduocate</l>
               <l>Whoſe vertue could the hardeſt penetrate,</l>
               <l>And make compaſſion eaſie, for her ſmile</l>
               <l>Could the ſad browes of ſterneſſe reconcile;</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:5277:23"/>
               <l>Her ſweetneſſe can the angry Ocean calme,</l>
               <l>And turne the Aſpe his poiſon into Balme,</l>
               <l>And ſtay the thunders heauy hand, iuſt then</l>
               <l>When it is threatning ruine to all men.</l>
               <l>The Tiger of her yong-ones robd would ſtay</l>
               <l>But at her preſence, and forbeare her prey.</l>
               <l>The angrieſt things muſt at her ſight appeare</l>
               <l>As ſmooth as Auguſt, or the ſpringing yeare.</l>
               <l>She the rich partner of his royall bed</l>
               <l>Who weares a triple crowne vpon his head.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Embrac'd</hi> him, cald him Lord, and at that word,</l>
               <l>Who could denie a pardon to afford.</l>
               <l>She ask'd, he gaue, and my deare fate in this</l>
               <l>Got my free pardon, ſhe a bountious kiſſe.</l>
               <l>So ſweetly ſeald was my remiſſe from death,</l>
               <l>So ratified by this ſo royall breath.</l>
               <l>Preſume not yet on this, occaſion ſo</l>
               <l>Will not her liberall aide to all beſtow,</l>
               <l>One thiefe was ſau'd, that no man ſhould deſpaire,</l>
               <l>But one, ſo that preſumptions forfeit are:</l>
               <l>He with his Sauiour died, bleſt time for him,</l>
               <l>Who elſe had found no pardon for his ſinne;</l>
               <l>I in my Soueraignes glory was to die,</l>
               <l>And that time ſet my life at liberty.</l>
               <l>Note the occaſions ſtrange that ſet vs free</l>
               <l>Me from this death, him to eternitie.</l>
               <l>My Prince's crowning, his Redeemers death,</l>
               <l>Aſſur'd his ſoule, and did reſtore my breath.</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:5277:24"/>
               <l>But euery day is not Coronation; Nor</l>
               <l>Did many ſuffer with our Sauiour.</l>
               <l>And mercy at ſuch times as theſe extended.</l>
               <l>To Iudgements turne, if grace be twice offended.</l>
               <l>And now you thinke me happy being free</l>
               <l>From death and ſhame by this benignitie,</l>
               <l>But if you doe a little backe reflect</l>
               <l>On the recharges of my foes, th' aſpect</l>
               <l>Of this ſun-ſhining day, you cloudy find</l>
               <l>And much foule weather in my face behind,</l>
               <l>For now, as I haue ſeene a tired Hare</l>
               <l>Of his owne ſwiftneſſe in a faint deſpaire,</l>
               <l>After whoſe fearefull feet, the yelping cry,</l>
               <l>Of the whole kennell, follow eagerly.</l>
               <l>Which ſpi'd, ſome Huntſman or ſome Shepheard neere,</l>
               <l>Seeing the weary <hi>Wat</hi> halfe dead with feare,</l>
               <l>In the Purſuers ſight, in his ſafe armes</l>
               <l>Folds the poore creature from their cruell harmes,</l>
               <l>'Bout whom the angry chaſers leape and bay,</l>
               <l>Aſſaulting him that keepes them from their prey,</l>
               <l>And with their fearefull noyſes fright it more,</l>
               <l>Then the poore beaſt was in purſuit before.</l>
               <l>Euen iuſt thus is my poore life purſu'de,</l>
               <l>Whilſt I thought danger paſt, it was renew'd</l>
               <l>For firſt they followed with much ſpeed, and cry,</l>
               <l>After poore mee (that fled but eaſily)</l>
               <l>And when the King of Forreſts and of Chaſes</l>
               <l>Thus found me deſtitute, before their faces,</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:5277:24"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>Ready to be deuour'd) ſnatch'd me away</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt then, as they were ſeizing on the prey,</l>
               <l>And in his royall armes of grace embrac'd</l>
               <l>My panting life, before ſo hotly chac'te,</l>
               <l>And yet behold my Aduerſaries rore</l>
               <l>With lowder exclamations, then before.</l>
               <l>And would with horrid clamours him conſtraine</l>
               <l>What he preſeru'd, thus to deſtroy againe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Appeales</hi> and <hi>Caueats,</hi> and ſuch things they bring</l>
               <l>To force me from the boſome of my King.</l>
               <l>On which diuineſt altar whilſt I hold</l>
               <l>I cannot be vnto their furies ſold.</l>
               <l>And yet the rareſt eloquence in Law</l>
               <l>That I could to my cauſes handling draw,</l>
               <l>I was enforc'd to craue; ſo ſtrongly they</l>
               <l>Did although pardon'd 'gainſt my life inuay.</l>
               <l>Here I a new muſt muſter vp my friends</l>
               <l>Wearied before; to croſſe their irefull ends.</l>
               <l>Make their endeauours ſuch to ſaue me now</l>
               <l>As if the King no Pardon did allow,</l>
               <l>Thus though my life they cannot take, you ſee</l>
               <l>They make me weary of 't by troubling mee.</l>
               <l>Thus a Delinquent muſt of force endure:</l>
               <l>He knowes not when he's freed; nor when ſecure.</l>
               <l>Behold, the Map of your proceeding heere,</l>
               <l>A Glaſſe in which to life, there doth appeare</l>
               <l>The forme of all your actions; vvhich I knovv</l>
               <l>Are vglier yet in ſubſtance then in ſhovv.</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:5277:25"/>
               <l>As they are vilde, your Aymes are worſe, your ends</l>
               <l>As bad againe, yet theſe your Hope tranſcends,</l>
               <l>For both in ill deſignes, it leads you on,</l>
               <l>And will moſt faile, when moſt you truſt vpon.</l>
               <l>☞ Now then if that you are not quite bereft</l>
               <l>Of likelihoods for grace, if there be left</l>
               <l>Roome but for one good thought, if vnto ſinne</l>
               <l>You haue not ſold your ſelues out-right, let in</l>
               <l>This motion I ſhall make, behold your fact,</l>
               <l>Summon your guilty conſcience, which is rackt</l>
               <l>And gladly would ſpeake truth, that it might gaine</l>
               <l>Eaſe to her ſelfe in her enſuing paine,</l>
               <l>She would account, and be diſcharg'd, thereby</l>
               <l>The worme a breeding would ſoone liue, ſoone die,</l>
               <l>A hideous horrid ſight it muſt needs bee,</l>
               <l>When in their vgly ſhapes, you chance to ſee</l>
               <l>Your monſtrous ſinnes appeare; yet happy men</l>
               <l>You cannot euer be at all till then:</l>
               <l>No nor then neither, if it be to late,</l>
               <l>'Tis ſome mens curſed and vnhappy fate,</l>
               <l>That they can ne're be touch'd at heart vntill</l>
               <l>The damned bed-roll of their ſinnes o're-fill</l>
               <l>Their guilty conſcience, in ſtead of prayer</l>
               <l>In vaine as they conceiue, they then deſpaire,</l>
               <l>Not able to appeale to Chriſt his paſſion,</l>
               <l>They greedily lay hold on their damnation.</l>
               <l>If not the feare of this your temporall death,</l>
               <l>Let the eternall moue, the one's but breath:</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:5277:25"/>
               <l>The other endleſſe, euer-liuing paine,</l>
               <l>Ere it be done, it ſtill begins againe,</l>
               <l>Pitty your ſilly ſoules, that elſe muſt frie</l>
               <l>In burning lakes of Brimſtome, neuer die</l>
               <l>Where worſe then <hi>Egypt's</hi> darkneſſe hems you in,</l>
               <l>With ſeuerall tortures for each vgly ſinne.</l>
               <l>Where howles, and hollow groanes the coapes-mates be</l>
               <l>To this eternall night of Miſerie.</l>
               <l>Where froſts, fires, drownings, ſulphur, choakings come</l>
               <l>Encreaſing ſtill, ne're ending; here's your doome.</l>
               <l>And theſe the torments that prepared are,</l>
               <l>Of which (vild men) you muſt expect your ſhare.</l>
               <l>If you will ſtill perſiſt, and not giue ore,</l>
               <l>'Tis then in vaine for to perſwade you more.</l>
               <l>I'le ceaſe my faire meanes therefore, and will try</l>
               <l>If I can fright you with an <hi>Hue and Cry,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here would I name both you, and your abode,</l>
               <l>But that you varie thoſe, on euery rode,</l>
               <l>Yo'are <hi>Eaſt,</hi> now <hi>Weſt,</hi> and next <hi>North</hi>-Country men,</l>
               <l>And then your names as oft you change agen.</l>
               <l>Thus to informe then, were to put in doubt,</l>
               <l>Not to giue light to men to finde you out.</l>
               <l>You in another kinde I will deſcribe,</l>
               <l>That euery man ſhall know you as you ride,</l>
               <l>Or to auoid you how, or his purſe loſt</l>
               <l>I teach you a true rule how he ſhall coaſt,</l>
               <l>And dogge you as you ride, how to be ſure</l>
               <l>To take you, when you thinke your ſelues ſecure.</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:5277:26"/>
               <l>☞ Becauſe I liu'd by ſpoyle of Paſſengers</l>
               <l>Thus will I recompence them, this worke's theirs</l>
               <l>Meant for their good, the guerdon for my gaine</l>
               <l>Is to aduiſe, how they may not ſuſtaine</l>
               <l>A farther loſſe, come be you rul'd by me,</l>
               <l>And well obſerue, theſe your inſtructions bee,</l>
               <l>When as you carrie charge, let no man know</l>
               <l>Nor of your money, nor yet when you goe.</l>
               <l>You haue a humour when you are to ride</l>
               <l>Your Neighbours Kinſmen, or your friends you bid</l>
               <l>To ſup, or breake their faſts, only to drinke</l>
               <l>Healths to your good returne, you little thinke</l>
               <l>There's any harme in this, yet I haue knowne</l>
               <l>A Father thus betray'd by his owne Sonne,</l>
               <l>A Brother by a Brother, and a friend</l>
               <l>Moſt deare in outward ſhew, to condeſcend.</l>
               <l>And lay the plot with theeues, bid them prepare</l>
               <l>Such a prize comes, whereof he takes a ſhare.</l>
               <l>Whilſt, but for him they neuer had bin met.</l>
               <l>Another kind of men there is, that ſet,</l>
               <l>Ten times more dangerous, you often chooſe</l>
               <l>Some one to guard you for feare you ſhould looſe</l>
               <l>Your money by the way, you doe relye</l>
               <l>Both on his valour, and his honeſtie,</l>
               <l>Now as you ride together, if he ſee</l>
               <l>You light on any other company,</l>
               <l>He rounds you in the eare (as if he tooke</l>
               <l>The greateſt care) and ſayes that you mans looke</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:5277:26"/>
               <l>He likes not, you perſwaded ſlacke your pace,</l>
               <l>So that alone he brings you to the place</l>
               <l>Where his confederates lie, and then ſurpris'd</l>
               <l>(As 'twas by him and them before deuis'd)</l>
               <l>They hacke, and hew againſt each others ſword,</l>
               <l>Till threatned to be <hi>ſhot,</hi> you giue the word,</l>
               <l>And bid him yeeld, (which he ſeemes loth to doe)</l>
               <l>Nay more he is inform'd which way they goe,</l>
               <l>And as you follow with an <hi>hue and Cry,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He will be ſure to leade you quite awry.</l>
               <l>☞ Oft in your Clothiers and your Graſiers Inne,</l>
               <l>You ſhall haue Chamberlaines, that there haue bin</l>
               <l>Plac'd purpoſely by theeues, or elſe conſenting</l>
               <l>By their large bribes, and by their often tempting,</l>
               <l>That marke your purſes drawne, and giue a geſſe</l>
               <l>What's there, within a little more or leſſe;</l>
               <l>Then will they gripe your cloak-bags, feele there weight</l>
               <l>There's likewiſe in my Hoſt ſometimes deceit,</l>
               <l>If it be left in charge with him all night,</l>
               <l>Vnto his roaring Gueſts he giues a light,</l>
               <l>(Who ſpend full thrice as much in wine and beare)</l>
               <l>As you in thoſe, and all your other cheare)</l>
               <l>Theſe inconueniences doe oft ariſe</l>
               <l>For want of heed, and care, be therefore wiſe.</l>
               <l>☞ Forbeare to ride vpon the Sabbath day,</l>
               <l>In which God ſayes, <hi>Remember,</hi> reſt, and pray,</l>
               <l>As we our ſeruants oftentimes command,</l>
               <l>When many buſineſſes they take in hand:</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:5277:27"/>
               <l>That chiefly one by no meanes they forget</l>
               <l>Aboue the reſt; iuſt thus much in effect</l>
               <l>Imports the word <hi>Remember,</hi> though our law</l>
               <l>Be not of force enough to keepe in awe</l>
               <l>The Sabbath-breaker, yet God in the way</l>
               <l>Oft meets with him, and giues him as a prey</l>
               <l>To high-way theeues, that day they rather chooſe</l>
               <l>Then any other, fitteſt for their vſe,</l>
               <l>For then the roads are quiet, and they know</l>
               <l>None ride but thoſe haue great affaires to doe,</l>
               <l>Which to effect, 'tis thought, they haue about them</l>
               <l>Great ſtore of Coyne, and this makes theeues miſdoubt them.</l>
               <l>And as the Cut-purſe is in prime of play,</l>
               <l>When men at Church doe moſt deuoutly pray,</l>
               <l>So are the High-way Cutters; for the <hi>Deuill</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is not content to tempt them to doe euill,</l>
               <l>But teaches them preſumption in the Act,</l>
               <l>Which well he knowes doth aggrauate the fact.</l>
               <l>Laſtly, if you are rob'd on that high day,</l>
               <l>It is not fit that then the Country pay</l>
               <l>Your money backe againe, that remedy,</l>
               <l>The Iudge in conſcience will to you deny,</l>
               <l>What reaſon is it men ſhould leaue to pray,</l>
               <l>To wait vpon your theeues that run away?</l>
               <l>☞ Noe, ride at lawfull times, and you ſhall meet</l>
               <l>Store of good company for you to keepe;</l>
               <l>Aſſociate though with none, vnleſſe with thoſe</l>
               <l>That you finde rather willing for to looſe</l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:5277:27"/>
               <l>Then haue your company; for they that ſtill</l>
               <l>Preſſe to be neere you, though againſt your will,</l>
               <l>Are ſomewhat dangerous; but I will ſhow</l>
               <l>How you ſhall finde if they be theeues, or no;</l>
               <l>Take but occaſion for to make ſome ſtay,</l>
               <l>Then marke; if that they keepe not on their way</l>
               <l>But ſlacke their pace, or elſe alight and goe;</l>
               <l>Or if perchance they doe refuſe to doe</l>
               <l>As I haue ſaid, iuſt then, before your face;</l>
               <l>Follow ſome halfe hower after, a ſlow pace;</l>
               <l>If ſo you ouer-take them, then take heed,</l>
               <l>For that's the very tricke of theeues indeed.</l>
               <l>Next of a theefe, the vſuall markes be theſe,</l>
               <l>(Which as you ride you may obſerue with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſe)</l>
               <l>They muffle with their cloakes, or elſe their coate</l>
               <l>Hides all their clothes, that ſo you may not note</l>
               <l>What ſutes they haue, a Handkercher they were</l>
               <l>About their neckes, or Cipreſſe, which they reare</l>
               <l>Ouer their mouthes, and noſes, with their hand</l>
               <l>Iuſt at the time, when as they bid you ſtand;</l>
               <l>Perhaps ſince here I haue diſcouered this,</l>
               <l>They will now leaue them off, that you may miſſe</l>
               <l>Your obſeruation, be you therefore ſure</l>
               <l>As ſoone as they come riding ſomewhat neere</l>
               <l>To gaze full at their faces, you ſhall ſee</l>
               <l>Them turne their heads away, as if ſo bee</l>
               <l>They had ſpide ſomething on the tother ſide,</l>
               <l>Which if they doe, then keepe your diſtance wide,</l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:5277:28"/>
               <l>But now they will not may be, yet may you</l>
               <l>Haue by theſe meanes a full and perfect view,</l>
               <l>And know them when you ſee them next, or whither</l>
               <l>Their great buſh beard, and face, agree together.</l>
               <l>This aboue all I wiſh you for your good,</l>
               <l>By any meanes ſhun him that weares a hood,</l>
               <l>Beware of them that whiſper, and thoſe men</l>
               <l>That are inquiſitiue, for ſurely then</l>
               <l>They but examine you that they may know</l>
               <l>By circumſtance, whe'r you haue coine or no.</l>
               <l>☞ You and your friend perchance doe ride together,</l>
               <l>Your company's increaſed by another,</l>
               <l>A ſeeming honeſt man, and you are glad</l>
               <l>Where's two to one ſuſpition none is had</l>
               <l>You call him fellow-trauellor, and he</l>
               <l>Reioyces in your honeſt companie,</l>
               <l>About ſome two miles riding there o're-takes</l>
               <l>Some three of his companions, then he ſhakes,</l>
               <l>Trembles, and quiuers, and ſeemes ſore afraid,</l>
               <l>And cries, directly friends we are way-laid,</l>
               <l>If you haue charge about you let me know,</l>
               <l>That I may cocke my Piſtoll as I goe,</l>
               <l>By thoſe, and ſuch like words, he will ſoone find,</l>
               <l>Whether, or no, your Purſe be richly lin'd,</l>
               <l>And whil'ſt you thought, there had been three to three,</l>
               <l>Your <hi>Iudas</hi> is on't 'other ſide you ſee.</l>
               <l>☞ Had you not need be wary, iudge I pray?</l>
               <l>Let me perſwade you, doe not ride by day</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:5277:28"/>
               <l>With any ſumme you are afraid to loſe</l>
               <l>But in the night, but then take heed of thoſe</l>
               <l>Baſe Padding Raſcalls, for their <hi>kill-calfe</hi> law</l>
               <l>I am not priuy to, I neuer ſaw</l>
               <l>Them, nor their actions, then I cannot ſhow</l>
               <l>How to preuent the thing I doe not know,</l>
               <l>But thus much I aſſure you, you are free</l>
               <l>From any horſmen you ſhall meet, or ſee,</l>
               <l>For they beleeue that none will ride at night,</l>
               <l>But onely thoſe whoſe Purſes are too light,</l>
               <l>And hardly worth the taking; next they muſt</l>
               <l>Keepe lawfull howers, for feare they through miſtruſt</l>
               <l>Be apprehended, that's their chiefeſt care;</l>
               <l>And then againe, I know they hardly dare</l>
               <l>Aduenture in the darke; for they can ſpie</l>
               <l>Neither aduantage, opportunitie,</l>
               <l>Nor whether you haue Piſtolls, nor yet know,</l>
               <l>Whether that you be likely men, or no,</l>
               <l>And you haue time your money to conuey,</l>
               <l>And much more benefit by night, then day.</l>
               <l>But ſince God hath ordain'd this time to reſt,</l>
               <l>And not to trauell in, I doe my beſt</l>
               <l>So to aduiſe you, that you ſhall be ſure</l>
               <l>What time ſo e're you ride, to be ſecure.</l>
               <l>☞ This is a generall rule, and obſeruation,</l>
               <l>Your high-way theeues doe alwaies keepe their ſtation</l>
               <l>Vpon your greateſt roads, that out of thoſe</l>
               <l>That do paſſe by, they may both picke and chooſe;</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:5277:29"/>
               <l>And ſo they cull the likelieſt out of many;</l>
               <l>But on your petty By-roads, where ſcarce any</l>
               <l>Are wont to trauell, they nere vſe to bee,</l>
               <l>You may be ſafe from any ieopardie</l>
               <l>If here you coaſt, which I aduiſe you to</l>
               <l>Rather then on your great high roads to go.</l>
               <l>☞ But aboue all which way ſo e're you ride,</l>
               <l>A Butts length diſtance at the leaſt diuide</l>
               <l>Your ſelues from one another, ſo keepe on,</l>
               <l>For I aſſure you they nere ſet vpon</l>
               <l>A ſcattered troope, for feare of ſomes eſcaping,</l>
               <l>Which may endanger their immediate taking,</l>
               <l>Beſides, their company they doe diuide</l>
               <l>And ſet at ſeuerall ſtands, and ſhould you ride</l>
               <l>All in a cluſter, they will ſally out</l>
               <l>Before, behinde, and compaſſe you about.</l>
               <l>Now if that following, they attempt, you ſpie</l>
               <l>Their drift and reſolution preſently.</l>
               <l>By their deuiſion, and haue time to ſhun</l>
               <l>The thing intended, ere it be begun.</l>
               <l>Beſides, they dare not doe but altogether,</l>
               <l>That they may be at hand with one another,</l>
               <l>To helpe where there's occaſion, ſay they ſhould</l>
               <l>Aduenture deſperately, they neuer could</l>
               <l>Bring you together, nor aſide the way;</l>
               <l>Without much trouble, and a greater ſtay;</l>
               <l>And peraduenture, ere halfe this be done,</l>
               <l>Vnto your reſcue there are others come.</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:5277:29"/>
               <l>Now I coniure you that ride by the while,</l>
               <l>Let neither threats nor faire words you beguile</l>
               <l>Nor yet diſwade, from yeelding your reliefe</l>
               <l>To thoſe you find in action with the thiefe,</l>
               <l>I doe remember I haue often beene</l>
               <l>Thus wickedly imploy'd, whilſt I haue ſeene</l>
               <l>Some others riding in to this our fray,</l>
               <l>I only wiſh'd them to keepe on their way,</l>
               <l>With ſuch perſwaſions, I found ſuted beſt</l>
               <l>With their amaze, ſee fairely thus diſtreſt</l>
               <l>And to our mercies, they haue left thoſe men</l>
               <l>That very cas'ly might haue reſcu'de beene.</l>
               <l>☞ Now thus much for preuention, here you ſee</l>
               <l>From point to point, a plaine diſcouerie,</l>
               <l>Of the theeues policie, I ſhew'd you how</l>
               <l>You may auoyde it, let me tell you now</l>
               <l>What you haue next to doe, If you eſpie</l>
               <l>(As you may gueſſe by my diſcouerie)</l>
               <l>That there are theeues amongſt you, doe not gaze</l>
               <l>On this, and tother ſide, nor in amaze</l>
               <l>Affrighted ſtand, as if your only hope</l>
               <l>Were ſome to reſcue you, that will prouoke</l>
               <l>And not diſhearten them, then minde it not,</l>
               <l>But be as though all feare you had forgot,</l>
               <l>And looke as bigge as they, and if they proffer</l>
               <l>Be ſure to draw, as ſoon's they make their offer</l>
               <l>Remember then the cauſe you haue in hand,</l>
               <l>Your reputation, and your money ſtand</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:5277:30"/>
               <l>At gage in this, and if you dare not fight,</l>
               <l>It grieues me much to doe you thus much right.</l>
               <l>They, (if they find you reſolute and ſtout)</l>
               <l>Dare euen aſwell be hang'd, as fight it out,</l>
               <l>Not out of cowardize, but that they know</l>
               <l>To their diſcomforts, that in fighting ſo</l>
               <l>They ſtriue againſt a Countrey, Iuſtice, Law,</l>
               <l>Right, equity, and theſe keepes them in awe.</l>
               <l>They ſtudie moſt, how they may bugbeares ſeeme,</l>
               <l>And who are rob'd, but thoſe that doe eſteeme</l>
               <l>Their threats, vnleſſe you yeeld without delay,</l>
               <l>We ſhoot you thorow, they perhaps may ſay;</l>
               <l>But who thus threatned, yet reſiſting ſtill</l>
               <l>Can ſay vnto me that he fared ill.</l>
               <l>Some though are ſome what reſolutely bent,</l>
               <l>Tis true, yet is it farre from their intent</l>
               <l>To ſhed your blood, for they in doing ſo,</l>
               <l>Should worke their owne immediate ouerthrow,</l>
               <l>They could not then ſubſiſt, for though they paſſe,</l>
               <l>Sought after ſlightly for the monies loſſe,</l>
               <l>Should they take life and all, they could not ride</l>
               <l>To any place where they might ſafely bide,</l>
               <l>But through continuall ſearch they would be found,</l>
               <l>And then pay dearly for each bloody wound.</l>
               <l>This the euent would be, which they well know,</l>
               <l>Rather then hurt you, they will let you goe,</l>
               <l>And ſtay a while vntill they meet with ſome</l>
               <l>Which their faire words, or threats will ouercome.</l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:5277:30"/>
               <l>Beſides, the right is of your ſide, and though</l>
               <l>You are o're-match'd, God may enable you ſo</l>
               <l>Thoſe Caytifes may be vanquiſh'd by your hand;</l>
               <l>Then what good ſeruice you ſhall doe your land,</l>
               <l>Your Prince, and Common-wealth, you may ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>Euen in the act by apprehending thoſe</l>
               <l>Who liue vpon the ſpoile, then hold them play</l>
               <l>And yours ſhall be the honour of the day.</l>
               <l>☞ But 'tis a fault of yours, you doe conſent</l>
               <l>And yeeld too patiently, you are content</l>
               <l>Not onely to be rob'd, but let them goe,</l>
               <l>And baſely wiſh they may eſcape, that ſo</l>
               <l>The Countrey may be lyable, for why</l>
               <l>If they not taken be with <hi>hue and cry,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You muſt haue all reſtor'd, and what care you:</l>
               <l>One thing more I will tell you, which is true,</l>
               <l>You often double and miſname the ſumme,</l>
               <l>You know the <hi>hundred</hi> willing is to come</l>
               <l>To compoſition with you, if they doe,</l>
               <l>You couſen both the theeues and Country too.</l>
               <l>And when you tell the ſtory, then although</l>
               <l>You were rob'd fairely, and but two to two,</l>
               <l>You ſay they were fiue, ſix, or at leaſt fower,</l>
               <l>And that you fought it out aboue an hower,</l>
               <l>And then you cut and ſlaſh your harmeleſſe clothes,</l>
               <l>And ſay that in the fight 'twas done by thoſe</l>
               <l>That tooke your money, which God knowes you gaue</l>
               <l>Without reſiſtance, ere they ſcarce did craue.</l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:5277:31"/>
               <l>Doe no more ſo, nor ſtriue that men may deeme</l>
               <l>You valiant, for it is a poore eſteeme</l>
               <l>To be accounted, if you be not ſo;</l>
               <l>And they haue farre a harder taske to doe</l>
               <l>To keepe opinion, falſly vndergone,</l>
               <l>Then thoſe haue none, for to atchieue to one.</l>
               <l>Be what your Images, doe repreſent,</l>
               <l>Men nobly ſpirited, 'twas God's intent</l>
               <l>When he created you, not much vnlike</l>
               <l>His Image moſt diuine, that you ſhould fight</l>
               <l>In a iuſt cauſe, becauſe he is all iuſt,</l>
               <l>And herein failing you betray God's truſt,</l>
               <l>Neglect your dutie, and doe animate</l>
               <l>Not curbe, the vild'ones, that doe perpetrate.</l>
               <l>☞ But now ſuppoſe through negligence you fall</l>
               <l>Into their clutches, and ſurpris'd with all</l>
               <l>You are vnthought of, 'tis no fault of mine</l>
               <l>You might haue taken better heed in time.</l>
               <l>Thus yet I will aduiſe you, if you ſee</l>
               <l>That you muſt yeeld and ouer-maſtred bee,</l>
               <l>Striue not at all, but giue the faireſt words</l>
               <l>Your beſt inuention and your wit affords,</l>
               <l>Wiſh that you had more monies, and withall</l>
               <l>Deliuer ſome, and ſo perhaps you ſhall</l>
               <l>By ſearching of your ſelues, and freeneſſe too,</l>
               <l>Without a further re-examining goe.</l>
               <l>But if they make an offer, doe not you</l>
               <l>Seeme to diſlike, what they doe meane to doe</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:5277:31"/>
               <l>Then will they ſift you ſoundly, doe not hold</l>
               <l>Your hand vpon your money, they are told</l>
               <l>Thus where it is, and ſurely they will gueſſe,</l>
               <l>They haue not all by your owne fearefulneſſe.</l>
               <l>I haue obſerued many times, when I</l>
               <l>Had tane ſuch money, as did ſatisfie,</l>
               <l>Out of the pocket hauing no intent</l>
               <l>To make a further ſearch, but only meant</l>
               <l>To lead the Paſſenger aſide the way,</l>
               <l>Becauſe I knew what danger 'twas to ſtay)</l>
               <l>Faſt'ning my clutches on his arme, or thigh,</l>
               <l>With a ſad looke, he would begin to cry</l>
               <l>He was vndone, if I tooke what was there,</l>
               <l>Thinking I felt (becauſe my hand was neere)</l>
               <l>His greater ſumme, which I by that ſhould find</l>
               <l>Hid in his ſleeue, or in his ſhirt behind.</l>
               <l>But now then, if they find not ſuch a ſumme</l>
               <l>As was expected, they will bid you come,</l>
               <l>Into ſome corner, then proteſt, and ſweare,</l>
               <l>If patiently a while, you will ſit there,</l>
               <l>You ſhall haue all reſtor'd, that they miſtooke</l>
               <l>You like are, but not thoſe, for whom they looke</l>
               <l>On theſe fond hopes you reſt, vntill that they</l>
               <l>Haue watch'd their time, and ſeiz'd another prey.</l>
               <l>To which you now are acceſſaries growne,</l>
               <l>But ſee where are their promiſes become?</l>
               <l>(Nor meant they otherwiſe) thoſe rifled to</l>
               <l>They take their Horſes and away they goe,</l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:5277:32"/>
               <l>And leaue you deſtitute, ſo with the reſt</l>
               <l>To tell the ſtorie whether fared beſt.</l>
               <l>☞ Yet looſe no time, but on with all the ſpeed</l>
               <l>That poſſible you can, and then take heed,</l>
               <l>It much concernes you, for when they eſpy</l>
               <l>That you purſue, the formoſt cunningly</l>
               <l>Falls into ſome by lane, 'tis vndeſcride</l>
               <l>For you ſuppoſe they altogether ride,</l>
               <l>So whilſt you thinke, you keepe at diſtance farre,</l>
               <l>A new amidſt them you ſurpriſed are.</l>
               <l>Here's their maine plot, you are forewarn'd, But ſay</l>
               <l>You cannot ouertake them, and that they</l>
               <l>Haue left the roade, and you in a great doubt,</l>
               <l>So that you know not how to finde them out,</l>
               <l>Let me direct you, I will inſtance thus,</l>
               <l>Suppoſe on <hi>Colebrooke</hi> way you loſe your purſe,</l>
               <l>The Theeues to <hi>Vxbridge</hi> roade, or <hi>Stanes</hi> will ride,</l>
               <l>And not to faile will there all night abide,</l>
               <l>This is the chiefeſt Maxime in their law,</l>
               <l>The Subt'leſt ſurely that I euer ſaw,</l>
               <l>It ſtands by reaſon, for they know full well</l>
               <l>None vſe to trauell thus athawrt to tell</l>
               <l>The Paſſages, or to deſcribe the men</l>
               <l>They reſt at pleaſure, and are gone agen</l>
               <l>Ere that the lazie-tithing <hi>hue and Cry</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Comes to enquire, and the authority</l>
               <l>Of ſome poore ſilly fellow, who is plac'd</l>
               <l>In that meane office, that he may be grac'd</l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:5277:32"/>
               <l>For double-diligence, oft as he goes</l>
               <l>Through wretched wilfulneſſe attaches thoſe</l>
               <l>That nere ment harme, yet being apprehended,</l>
               <l>They often loſe their liues, though ne're offended.</l>
               <l>But to deale ſafe and ſure, without delay</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>coure you the next great right and left hand way,</l>
               <l>And if at night you miſſe, a carefull ſpy</l>
               <l>Next day ſhall ſurely ſee them riding by.</l>
               <l>Grant Now they leaue this cuſtome, all their art,</l>
               <l>Their wit, inuention, neuer can impart</l>
               <l>The like againe, I vow, I doe not ſee</l>
               <l>Whither they can be take them to be free</l>
               <l>But by the way know thus much, if they light</l>
               <l>On a great ſumme, then will they ride that night</l>
               <l>Vnto their <hi>Rendeuous</hi> here in the City,</l>
               <l>Which is too ſure a ſhelter, (more's the pitty.)</l>
               <l>But follow my aduiſe, and marke me well,</l>
               <l>For here a cunning plot of theirs I tell,</l>
               <l>If you are rob'd out in the Eaſterne quarter,</l>
               <l>When you with <hi>hue and cry</hi> the theeues make after,</l>
               <l>Ride not to <hi>London</hi> in the roade you were,</l>
               <l>Nor raiſe thoſe parts, you will not finde them there,</l>
               <l>But hie to <hi>Weſtminſter, Holborne,</hi> the <hi>Strand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And for a ſpeedy ſearch there giue command,</l>
               <l>If Northward they light on you, ſtraightwayes ride</l>
               <l>And ſearch both <hi>Southwarke, Lambeth,</hi> &amp; <hi>Banckeſide,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus they doe alwaies plant themſelues, for ſo</l>
               <l>They haue the Citty betwixt them and you.</l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:5277:33"/>
               <l>And ere your ſearch comes at them (by the way</l>
               <l>Which often dyes) there's time at will to ſtay.</l>
               <l>I haue obſeru'd (and it is ſtill in vſe,</l>
               <l>Nor will it ere reforme the vild abuſe</l>
               <l>It hath a leuell at) a needleſſe care</l>
               <l>Wherewith all ſorts of people troubled are,</l>
               <l>And charged too, when any one hath loſt</l>
               <l>His purſe to theeues, then at the Countries coſt</l>
               <l>There is a watch prepar'd to guard that place</l>
               <l>Where the poore man by them ſurpriſed was;</l>
               <l>This is like ſhutting vp the Stable doore,</l>
               <l>When as the Horſe was ſtolne out before,</l>
               <l>'Tis not to be ſuppos'd the thiefe will come</l>
               <l>And make a needleſſe breach, to thanke the Groome</l>
               <l>For feeding of the beſt; loe then iuſt ſo,</l>
               <l>Nor meane the high-way theeues that way to goe</l>
               <l>Where there is waite laid for them, ſay they ſhould;</l>
               <l>I doe proteſt here; I did euer hold</l>
               <l>(And found it by experience) that high-way</l>
               <l>That had a watch vpon it, beſt for prey.</l>
               <l>For firſt the honeſt Trauellers ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>It is impoſſible, that they ſhould loſe</l>
               <l>Their money being guarded thus; and hence</l>
               <l>They grow more careleſſe, doubting none offence</l>
               <l>Can any wayes betyde them; whilſt alaſſe</l>
               <l>A thiefe may doe his liſt, and freely paſſe,</l>
               <l>The watchmen neere the wiſer; for they ſtand</l>
               <l>Setled at one place by a ſtrict command.</l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:5277:33"/>
               <l>It is indifferent when the theefe layes hold,</l>
               <l>His booty ſingled out, he will make bold</l>
               <l>To ſeize him any where; all places are</l>
               <l>All one alike to him, he will not care</l>
               <l>So that the coaſt be cleare, and then how can</l>
               <l>He be diſtinguiſh' from an honeſt man?</l>
               <l>I neuer paſt by, but the watchmen gaue</l>
               <l>Me courteous language, wiſhing me to haue</l>
               <l>A ſpeciall care I was not rob'd; whil'ſt I</l>
               <l>Was a chiefe actor of that villanie.</l>
               <l>But now ſuppoſe they had examin'd me,</l>
               <l>I would haue anſwer'd them ſo courteouſly,</l>
               <l>That they could not ſuſpect. Now what are they</l>
               <l>That are appointed watchmen for the way?</l>
               <l>Poore, ſilly, old, decrepped men, that are</l>
               <l>Fitting for nought elſe, but to loyter there;</l>
               <l>Haue not I ſeene a dozen ſuch, all ſtand</l>
               <l>(With each of them a Holbert in his hand)</l>
               <l>Amaz'd, affrighted, and durſt neuer quatch,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt we before their faces all; did catch,</l>
               <l>Aſſault, ſeize, rifle ſuch as did paſſe by,</l>
               <l>When we were gone (perhaps) then would they cry</l>
               <l>Theefes, theefes, (to little purpoſe) I haue knowne</l>
               <l>Some that by way of parly, thus haue growne</l>
               <l>Familiar with the watch, and as they found</l>
               <l>A fit occaſion, they haue tane, and bound</l>
               <l>The ſilly fellowes hand, and foot; then ſtood</l>
               <l>Like a ſafe guard ſet for the Countries good,</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:5277:34"/>
               <l>With browne bils in their hands, and ſo made bold</l>
               <l>(As with authority) to ſtop, and hold</l>
               <l>All that did come that way, I doe ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>A watch of Holbarteers were good for thoſe</l>
               <l>Foot-padding-night theeues) but for theſe you ſee</l>
               <l>Such care, and trouble all in vaine will bee.</l>
               <l>But if you will needs haue it ſo, chooſe then</l>
               <l>Strong, able, ſtout, and reſolute young men,</l>
               <l>Arme them with Bow, and Arrowes, Muſcets, Shot,</l>
               <l>And with a Horſe or two, that they may not</l>
               <l>Be thus abuſ'd, but if occaſion be</l>
               <l>May follow on to purpoſe; but by me</l>
               <l>And mine inſtructions here, I hope you ſhall</l>
               <l>Be well ſecur'd, and need no watch at all.</l>
               <l>☞ I thinke it fitting now for me to ſhow</l>
               <l>Vnto the Inne-keeper, how he ſhall know</l>
               <l>Such gueſts from other men, my Hoſt take heed,</l>
               <l>To winke at ſuch faults were a fault indeed,</l>
               <l>Reſpect then rather honeſty, then gaine.</l>
               <l>Know well your ſeruants whom you entertaine,</l>
               <l>Trie them, that you may truſt, their helpe in this</l>
               <l>Subtill diſcouery, moſt needfull is.</l>
               <l>Your Oſtler muſt obſerue, and he ſhall ſee</l>
               <l>About their horſes, they will curious bee</l>
               <l>They muſt be ſtrangely dreſt, as ſtrangely fed</l>
               <l>With Maſhes, prouender, and Chriſtians bred;</l>
               <l>If this be wondred at, they cannot hold,</l>
               <l>Their goodly qualities they muſt vnſold,</l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:5277:34"/>
               <l>Crying, they doe deſerue it, and that they</l>
               <l>By their good ſeruice will their coſt repay</l>
               <l>With ouer-plus, or ſome words more or leſſe,</l>
               <l>By which relation he may ſhrewdly gueſſe.</l>
               <l>And then they will be asking, who is he</l>
               <l>That ownes that horſe? and whoſe thoſe horſes be</l>
               <l>That ſtand beyond him? what their Maſters are?</l>
               <l>What kind of men? whither they ride? how farre?</l>
               <l>And when? ſo by his anſweres they ſurmize</l>
               <l>Which of them all will be their likelieſt prize.</l>
               <l>Next of their Cloak-bags let him notice take,</l>
               <l>They onely carry them for faſhion's ſake,</l>
               <l>For they are empty ones, in pollicie,</l>
               <l>Becauſe their horſes ſhould not laden be.</l>
               <l>Your Chamberlaine ſhall finde, when as they come</l>
               <l>Vſher'd vp by him to their Lodging roome,</l>
               <l>He ſhall be ſent away, let him giue eare,</l>
               <l>And not to faile, he ſhall be ſure to heare</l>
               <l>The gingling of their money, Let him pry</l>
               <l>Behind ſome ſecret Cranies priuily,</l>
               <l>And he ſhall ſee them ſhare, what they haue got,</l>
               <l>And euery one to take what is his lot.</l>
               <l>This they by no meanes will deferre, for feare,</l>
               <l>Who has the purſe, ſhould cheat them in the ſhare;</l>
               <l>This done, they hug each other, next they call</l>
               <l>Their rauiſh'd ſences home, and then withall</l>
               <l>They knocke againe for him, who ſhall be ſhent</l>
               <l>For not attending, though enioyn'd he went.</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:5277:35"/>
               <l>Now muſt he draw a cup of curious Sacke,</l>
               <l>Then next mine Hoaſt your company they lacke,</l>
               <l>With farre-fetcht complements they will ſalute</l>
               <l>And bid you welcome, marke from their diſpute</l>
               <l>What you can gather, you may ſomewhat gueſſe</l>
               <l>By their mens ſawcy peremptorineſſe,</l>
               <l>For ſeruants when their Maſters ills they know</l>
               <l>Ceaſe their obedience, and preſumptious grow.</l>
               <l>Enquire a part, each ones particular name,</l>
               <l>And let your ſeuerall ſeruants doe the ſame,</l>
               <l>And you ſhall finde them tripping, they well may</l>
               <l>Forget the new names, that they tooke that day;</l>
               <l>At ſupper time let ſome one haſtily</l>
               <l>Knocke at your gate, as with authority,</l>
               <l>You ſhall obſerue a ſudden fearefull ſtart,</l>
               <l>Marke then their lookes (the Index of the heart)</l>
               <l>And you ſhall finde them troubled, looke you ſad,</l>
               <l>And aske if yonder Conſtable be mad?</l>
               <l>Bid them ſay quickly, what their danger is,</l>
               <l>Then promiſe no authority of his</l>
               <l>Shall enter there, if they command it ſo,</l>
               <l>By this, into their priuate thoughts you go,</l>
               <l>They will confeſſe for ſuccour, needs no more,</l>
               <l>'Tis euident what you but thought before,</l>
               <l>But ſay hereafter they ſhould careleſſe grow,</l>
               <l>Then are they taken with the leſſe adoe.</l>
               <l>Now ſay they come about the noone of day,</l>
               <l>You ſhall well know them, by their needleſſe ſtay,</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:5277:35"/>
               <l>Their careleſneſſe of time, for they but bait,</l>
               <l>That they may ſtand at gaze, and fitly wait</l>
               <l>For honeſt paſſengers, when they haue ſpide</l>
               <l>A likely-moneyd booty by them ride,</l>
               <l>Then will they buſſle, and make haſt away</l>
               <l>With farre more ſpeed then tedious was their ſtay.</l>
               <l>And cry yon rides their Vncle, or their friend</l>
               <l>With whom ſome earneſt buſineſſe they pretend;</l>
               <l>When in an Inne, they muſt all-night abide,</l>
               <l>They cunningly, ſometimes themſelues diuide</l>
               <l>And come as ſeuerall companies, thereby</l>
               <l>To croſſe the number in the <hi>Hue and Cry.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Beſides thus parted, they are ſure to know</l>
               <l>If otherwiſe then well, the ſquares ſhould goe,</l>
               <l>They of each other will no notice take</l>
               <l>Of you (mine Hoſt) they will enquirie make</l>
               <l>What their companions are? what Countrimen?</l>
               <l>Whether you know them yea or no? and then</l>
               <l>If they can finde you haue a Ielouſie</l>
               <l>Shrewdly ſuſpecting either company,</l>
               <l>Hauing diſcouered your opinion</l>
               <l>With all conuenient ſpeed, they will get gone,</l>
               <l>But if you doe (as well you may) miſtake them</l>
               <l>And that for honeſt trauellers you take them,</l>
               <l>They (as by chance) will in your kitchen meet,</l>
               <l>And as meere ſtrangers, one another greet,</l>
               <l>There will they drinke together, ere they goe</l>
               <l>From thence, ſo louing and ſo kinde they grow</l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:5277:36"/>
               <l>That they will ſup togeather, marke them well</l>
               <l>And you their cunning knauery ſhall ſmell.</l>
               <l>Still ſtrangers to each other will they bee,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt any of your houſe are there to ſee;</l>
               <l>But ſee, and be not ſeene, and you ſhall finde</l>
               <l>Them all familiar in another kinde,</l>
               <l>They will Embrace, reioyce, laugh at their plot</l>
               <l>And at mine Hoſt that he ſuſpects it not.</l>
               <l>The faireſt Innes they vſually frequent,</l>
               <l>Out of a wary-politicke intent,</l>
               <l>Preſuming, for diſparaging the man</l>
               <l>They will not ſearch his howſe, and the re they can</l>
               <l>Reſt vnmoleſted, but ſince this you know</l>
               <l>Let not the ſubtile theefe, eſcape you ſo.</l>
               <l>☞ Loe here I haue vnclaſp'd this obſcure booke,</l>
               <l>And full Quotations on thoſe ſecrets tooke,</l>
               <l>That the plaine eye of Iudging reaſon, may</l>
               <l>Diſcouer ſuch abuſes of the way,</l>
               <l>And as 'tis ſaid, that true repenters muſt</l>
               <l>Their ſecret ſinnes, and all ills from them thruſt,</l>
               <l>Leſt the vild tainture of one crime behinde</l>
               <l>Contaminate againe the ſinfull minde,</l>
               <l>Thus haue I left no nooke, no cranny ſmall,</l>
               <l>Which men may cunning or pernicious call</l>
               <l>Vn-open'd here, before the curious day</l>
               <l>As cleere and plaine, as is the Champion way,</l>
               <l>No act, or vſe which the eues diſcouer might,</l>
               <l>No Art, to make the honeſt know them right,</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:5277:36"/>
               <l>Leſt by retaining ought, it might be deem'd,</l>
               <l>My true recanting is not, what it ſeem'd.</l>
               <l>But marke my cautions well, and you will know</l>
               <l>That theſe way-riflers muſt ſome new way goe</l>
               <l>Imagination, or their practice yet</l>
               <l>Could neuer reach to, or before you ſet</l>
               <l>Preuention of their worſt aſſaults, their drifts</l>
               <l>In their attempt, and their beſt ſcaping ſhifts.</l>
               <l>Nor can I feare, but ſince ſo freely I</l>
               <l>Haue here diſſected ſuch impietie,</l>
               <l>Anatomizing euery hidden Nerue</l>
               <l>That for the ſtrength of ſuch occaſions ſerue,</l>
               <l>The charitable world will hence allow,</l>
               <l>That I thoſe men and actions diſauow</l>
               <l>I make ſo plaine and hatefull, nor againe</l>
               <l>Will I my honour in thoſe puddles ſtaine,</l>
               <l>Nor can it be ſuppoſ'd by enuie, that</l>
               <l>Any relap's of mine be aimed at,</l>
               <l>For mine owne writ, muſt then in Iudgement ſtand</l>
               <l>And ſigne me vnto death, mine owne falſe hand;</l>
               <l>The Iurie, and the Iudge, in Euidence,</l>
               <l>Shall no enquiry need for mine offence,</l>
               <l>This booke alone againſt all pittie's plea,</l>
               <l>Turnes all excuſe into Apoſtrophe,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt dumbe as death, with double ſhame I muſt</l>
               <l>Count both my ruine, and my ſentence iuſt.</l>
               <l>Now let detracting cenſure, pawſe, and ſtay</l>
               <l>And turne their rank'rous ſpleenes another way,</l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:5277:37"/>
               <l>And know that now in Cenſure, they doe more</l>
               <l>Then I haue done in all the reſt before,</l>
               <l>When my determin'd Innocence ſhalbee</l>
               <l>A Iudge ſeuere againſt their cruelty;</l>
               <l>☞ And ſuch whoſe moſt vnneceſſary eye,</l>
               <l>Into forbidden acts of others pry,</l>
               <l>And when the man they curiouſly haue read,</l>
               <l>Muſt then attempt the ſecrets of his bed,</l>
               <l>To poyſon all his bleſſings, nicely draw</l>
               <l>The Curtaines, whoſe concealings no man ſaw</l>
               <l>Without a rude intruding, for the bed</l>
               <l>Of lawfull couples being iniured</l>
               <l>By baſe detractions, leades that troubled ſence</l>
               <l>Into the fulleſt foulneſſe of offence;</l>
               <l>And ſo my pillowes partner, to whoſe truth</l>
               <l>I owe the beſt reforming of my youth,</l>
               <l>As if ſhe muſt be ſharer of my wrongs,</l>
               <l>Though ne're arraign'd was yet condemn'd by tongs.</l>
               <l>As if of force becauſe ſhee's mine, ſhe muſt</l>
               <l>In ſpight of all her vertue be vniuſt,</l>
               <l>But I imagine rather this ſurmize,</l>
               <l>Doth from the common ground of ill ariſe,</l>
               <l>Or from that Enuy, <hi>Sathan</hi> left behind,</l>
               <l>When he infected our firſt mothers mind:</l>
               <l>Shew me the man whoſe tendreſt, deareſt loue,</l>
               <l>And whoſe affection in a ſtraine doth moue</l>
               <l>Beyond community, vnto his wife,</l>
               <l>Who but in her, has neither ſoule, nor life,</l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:5277:37"/>
               <l>And giue me reaſons why his ſhould tranſcend</l>
               <l>The debt I owe to mine vnequall friend?</l>
               <l>Then will I yeeld my dotage, his loue rare,</l>
               <l>And thus our obligations I compare.</l>
               <l>Firſt, vnto you whoſe marriages intent</l>
               <l>Haue to the fortune of your choice extent</l>
               <l>More then the perſon, or thoſe faire deſerts</l>
               <l>Which make the bleſſedſt contracts of the hearts,</l>
               <l>And loue the purchaſe more of her eſtate</l>
               <l>Then her perſections, you ne're leaueld at;</l>
               <l>You who were neuer caught with darting eies,</l>
               <l>Whoſe beſt affections in her treaſure lies,</l>
               <l>And neuer had your ſoules with loue refin'd,</l>
               <l>Peruerting the true vſe of either kind,</l>
               <l>Can yet in this your portions dotage, not</l>
               <l>Exceed the Income I by mine haue got.</l>
               <l>For when I was adiudg'd, and doom'd to die,</l>
               <l>She onely by ſtrange importunitie</l>
               <l>Melted the hearts of all reſolu'd againſt mee,</l>
               <l>Who pittying her, ſet my lifes danger free,</l>
               <l>In this my life, my fortune, and my all,</l>
               <l>I may her portion, and her bleſſing call.</l>
               <l>And laſt for other tyes, which doe obliege</l>
               <l>Such as to loues faire fortreſſes lay ſiege</l>
               <l>The ſimpathizing liking, and thoſe parts</l>
               <l>Of loues religion, which locks louers hearts</l>
               <l>Was throwne on me, and theſe who can diſproue,</l>
               <l>Muſt either haue no heart, or know no loue:</l>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:5277:38"/>
               <l>In pitty then, to <hi>Citharaea's</hi> Shrine</l>
               <l>All you that ſacrifice your thoughts diuine,</l>
               <l>Since we are pleaſ'd, let none our peace moleſt,</l>
               <l>Nor breake the Vnion of ſo ſweet a reſt,</l>
               <l>With nice inquiry, after things, you muſt</l>
               <l>Confeſſe you haue no buſineſſe with, that's iuſt,</l>
               <l>And we ſhall be, if you but leaue vs ſo,</l>
               <l>More happy, then 'tis fit for you to know.</l>
               <l>☞ Yet for my ſelfe, beleeue I haue the ſence</l>
               <l>Of mine owne youth's abuſing, and offence</l>
               <l>Which I haue wrought againſt the Common-weale,</l>
               <l>Whoſe wounds by this relation I may heale,</l>
               <l>If my aduice be follow'd, you will ſee</l>
               <l>The ſoule vnlac'd of high-way ſubtiltie.</l>
               <l>That who ſhall ſuffer now, in ſuch offence,</l>
               <l>Has none to blame but his owne negligence,</l>
               <l>I doe beſides my pretious youth lament,</l>
               <l>My reput's forfeit, ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſhment,</l>
               <l>The deare miſpences of my faireſt time,</l>
               <l>Conuerting all my bleſſings into crime,</l>
               <l>My wit, my Iudgement, ſtrength, courage, and all</l>
               <l>Vnto my Countries miſchiefe, mine owne fall.</l>
               <l>Nor doe I thinke it halfe enough that I</l>
               <l>Barely confeſſe mine owne impiety,</l>
               <l>And talking onely to the people ſhew</l>
               <l>Thoſe guilts, perhaps before I ſpeake, they know</l>
               <l>Or with a ſuperficiall gloſſe thus ſeeme</l>
               <l>To flatter men into a faire eſteeme</l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:5277:38"/>
               <l>Of my beſt promiſ'd actions, whoſe euent</l>
               <l>Might proue the ſpeakers of a worſe intent;</l>
               <l>No, naked as firſt <hi>Adam's</hi> Innocence,</l>
               <l>I ſtrip the deform'd ſhape of mine offence,</l>
               <l>Diſlodging from my heart that baniſht ſpirit,</l>
               <l>That can no dwelling there againe inherit,</l>
               <l>And on iuſt cauſe diuorc'd from ſuch a bride,</l>
               <l>Can hardly now it's memory abide,</l>
               <l>Me thinkes thus purg'd, I hate the very roome</l>
               <l>Which that vild Inmates lodging was become,</l>
               <l>And as the bodies glorified, ſcorne</l>
               <l>The thoughts of ioyes wherewith their frailty's borne.</l>
               <l>Deſpiſing as it were the fulleſt things</l>
               <l>Which the dull earth to our admiring brings;</l>
               <l>So my refined ſoule, and my cleare minde</l>
               <l>Can in theſe vild companions no peace finde,</l>
               <l>But troubled at the old acquaintance grow,</l>
               <l>Thought-ſick, that e're ſuch practice they did know.</l>
               <l>Or as the <hi>Epicure,</hi> whoſe working wiſh</l>
               <l>Is dreaming ſtill vpon ſome curious diſh,</l>
               <l>On which, his waking thoughts, and ſleepe imploy'd</l>
               <l>Are buſily, vntill it be enioy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</l>
               <l>Which purchac'd, his diſcretion is farre leſſe</l>
               <l>Then was his couet ere he did poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>For gluttonizing his o're-charged cheſt,</l>
               <l>He neither can vngorge, nor yet digeſt,</l>
               <l>Till ſurfeited to death, he loaths it more</l>
               <l>Then ere he did embrace, or loue before.</l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:5277:39"/>
               <l>So I whoſe eaſie youth, with fond admire,</l>
               <l>Was drawne, at firſt this ill courſe to deſire,</l>
               <l>Hug'd it in dreames, and in my waking fits</l>
               <l>Doted vpon't, to my worſe loſſe of wits,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt I eſteem'd none braue, or good, but this,</l>
               <l>But now I know how farre I was amiſſe.</l>
               <l>And ſurfeited, as 'twere to death indeed,</l>
               <l>From which by rare ingredients I am freed.</l>
               <l>I loath my ſtomacke-queller, and abhorre</l>
               <l>What I in too much louing ſufferd for,</l>
               <l>Nor can profeſſion free me from the doome</l>
               <l>Of cruel'ſt cenſure and opinion,</l>
               <l>Theſe actuall ills of mine freely confeſs'd</l>
               <l>Muſt be in act recouer'd, or expreſt</l>
               <l>My faire intentions cannot be, nor I</l>
               <l>Sau'd from the taxe of my firſt infamie.</l>
               <l>☞ O may my fate ſo well prouide as now</l>
               <l>That power which knowes, may helpe me in my vow,</l>
               <l>And crowne my reſolutions with ſome way</l>
               <l>Which of the world, and heauen recouer may</l>
               <l>All my loſt honour, by ſome acts of mine,</l>
               <l>That may proue farre more welcome to the time.</l>
               <l>Then my diſaſtrous courſes, and expreſſe</l>
               <l>I am much better then I dare profeſſe.</l>
               <l>And that great king, whoſe mercy, goodneſſe, grace,</l>
               <l>Hath fixt my tottering life in a firme place,</l>
               <l>Whoſe royall bounty do's I know expect</l>
               <l>From my ſo great enioying, ſome effect</l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:5277:39"/>
               <l>Which may a thankfull tribute pay to him,</l>
               <l>And ſpeake the full redemption of my ſinne.</l>
               <l>You, mightie Sir, to whom my life I owe</l>
               <l>As debt to that great grace you did beſtowe,</l>
               <l>May now command it proſtrate at your feet</l>
               <l>In any danger, (I ſhall haſte to meet)</l>
               <l>That ſo by ſeruing in your enterpriſe,</l>
               <l>You may perceiue how true a ſacrifice</l>
               <l>Ile make againe, of what you gaue ſo free,</l>
               <l>And that's the offering muſt accepted bee.</l>
               <l>I hope (great Sir) it is not your intent</l>
               <l>That I ſhall ſpend my dayes in Baniſhment,</l>
               <l>For happier farre is he condemn'd that dies,</l>
               <l>Then him you ſaue t'exile from your faire eies.</l>
               <l>For what auailes the blinded man to ſee,</l>
               <l>If that a dungeon muſt his priſon bee?</l>
               <l>Where doubly curſ'd to be debarr'd from light</l>
               <l>He dwells, that knew't not, whil'ſt he wanted ſight,</l>
               <l>O let me liue, where euery day I may</l>
               <l>My moſt religious offrings truely pay;</l>
               <l>And that the life you gaue me, be not made</l>
               <l>A trouble to me, whil'ſt my thoughts inuade</l>
               <l>My diſcontented ſoule with torments ſtrange;</l>
               <l>Not that I muſt my aire, and Country change,</l>
               <l>Or (bard inheriting thereby) forgoe</l>
               <l>The temporall fortunes I am borne vnto.</l>
               <l>But that the Shryne I worſhip ſhould not ſee</l>
               <l>The conſtant ſacrifice is made by mee.</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:5277:40"/>
               <l>Me thinkes could doe more then common men,</l>
               <l>(For no ſuch obligation ſtrengthens them)</l>
               <l>That my <hi>Prince</hi> might his owne great power know,</l>
               <l>In ſeruice I could doe vpon his foe;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So let me liue, that vent'ring ſo to die,</l>
               <l>I pay my debt, and ſuffer happilie.</l>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Viuit poſt funera, virtus.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:5277:40"/>
            <head>To the Kings moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, <hi>John Clauell</hi> wiſheth a long, and proſperous reigne in this, and in the world to come, a plenteous ſhare of thoſe peculiar bleſſings, which God himſelfe (out of his wonderfull and abundant goodnes) hath prouided and ſet apart (euen for the choiſeſt of his elect) which are farre beyond the imagniation of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men to conceiue, much more impoſſible to be expreſſed.</head>
            <l>IT grieues my ſoule, and wounds my troubled minde,</l>
            <l>That onely I alone muſt be confinde,</l>
            <l>When others are let looſe, that they may gaine</l>
            <l>The honour they haue loſt, whil'ſt my foule ſtaine</l>
            <l>Blurres both my birth, and fortunes; had I dide,</l>
            <l>My ignominious death had ſatisfide;</l>
            <l>But to liue ſtill, and ſtill to liue in ſhame,</l>
            <l>(Within the ſummons of vpbraiding fame)</l>
            <l>Is a worſe plague then euer Egypt had;</l>
            <l>It may be thought, I that haue beene ſo bad</l>
            <l>Cannot recant, but very likely may</l>
            <l>Fall to my old rebellion, on the way;</l>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:5277:41"/>
            <l>Firſt let this treaty plead; then here I call</l>
            <l>My God aboue to witneſſe (who knowes all</l>
            <l>The ſecrets of my heart) I doe intend</l>
            <l>Whilſt theſe your warres endure, euen there to ſpend</l>
            <l>My time, in that braue ſeruice; when that ends</l>
            <l>(If I chance to ſuruiue) I haue then friends,</l>
            <l>And a poore fortune of my owne, that can</l>
            <l>Fairely maintaine me, like an honeſt man;</l>
            <l>If ſo your Highneſſe pleaſe, that I may haue</l>
            <l>My gratious pardon, (you ſo freely gaue)</l>
            <l>What is required of me, I cannot pay,</l>
            <l>If that the meanes wherewith be kept away;</l>
            <l>Confinde within theſe walls, is it your will</l>
            <l>That I a priſoner here, continue ſtill?</l>
            <l>When I was paſt the cure, and helpe of men,</l>
            <l>You (that could onely) ſhielded me, iuſt then</l>
            <l>When death had taken leuell with his dart,</l>
            <l>Was it that I might feele this greater ſmart?</l>
            <l>O no; I neuer ſince haue beg'd that boone,</l>
            <l>But you (great Sir) haue granted it right ſoone;</l>
            <l>Yet notwithſtanding your moſt royall pleaſure,</l>
            <l>I am enforc'd to tarry others leaſure,</l>
            <l>Like <hi>Tantalus,</hi> in this my hell I ſee,</l>
            <l>And know the grace you haue beſtowd on me,</l>
            <l>But may not touch it, and enioy much leſſe,</l>
            <l>The more's my griefe, and my vnhappineſſe,</l>
            <l>O free me from this lingring lethergie,</l>
            <l>Set me at liberty, or let me die.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:5277:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
